当我第一次看到这个片头的时候
SYLVESTER STALLONE: I remember the first time I saw these credits.
心想：天啊 我们实在把目标定得太高了
I thought, "My God. We're really setting the bar high.''
我从来没见过这样一部小电影
I'd never seen such large credits
使用这么大的标题
for such a little movie in my life.
"1975年11月25日 费城”
我记得影片一开始是一副耶稣画像
Kind of interesting the way it started out with this shot of Jesus.
我想是代表着运动员的复活 然后镜头向下移动 我们看到了洛奇的脸
I guess, in Resurrection Athletic Club, who then it comes down to Rocky's face, there.
我觉得他可能是被上帝选中的
So, I suppose the die was cast that he was the chosen one,
下一个要拯救或让他复生的人
the next one to maybe be saved or resurrected.
这看起来用了很多直喻的手法
It was kind of like some heavy-handed symbolism,
不过最后总是很有用
but it all seemed to work in the end.
拳击场上的对手是南美冠军 凯佐·拉威尔
The fellow I'm in the ring with is the South American Champion, Pedro Lovell,
他个头很大 身高大约有6尺5
who is actually quite large. He's almost like 6'5''.
他打拳的时候没有站直
But he fought in a way that it was believable.
因为我身高5尺10
'Cause I'm like 5'10''.
所以这是一个很棒的组合
So it was a pretty good combination.
加油！加油！
Hit him! Hit him!
洛奇让自己被对手痛击
He let himself be hit pretty hard
直到自己的潜能爆发出来
and lent himself to the kind of ragey, un-sophistication of Rocky.
洛奇对他乱打一通 没有任何技巧
It was like Rocky just hit from every angle and had no skills whatsoever,
只是表现出一种求生意志
except this unbelievable need to survive.
你在闪避 得给他一点颜色
You're waltzing. Give the sucker some action.
老教练在向他提建议
No corner men to speak of, just strangers offering him real bad advice.
这是他的人生
This is his life.
快喝啤酒吧！
VENDOR: Cold beer here!
洛奇 我敢说不会超过三回合 你能坚持吗？
Should I bet the fight don't go three rounds? You feel strong?
- 没问题   - 冰啤酒！
-Absolutely. -Cold beer!
相信这其实是在电影当中
This actually, I believe, was the last scene
最后拍摄的一幕
filmed in the movie.
你现在所看到的 其实是最后一幕
We start off with it, but it's actually the last one.
在拍摄现场 那是我体重最轻的时候
When production started, I was at my lightest weight.
我们已经经历过了一场大战
We had already been through the big fight.
所以可以说…
So, you might say I was
我已经筋疲力尽 几乎想要放弃
pretty well overdue to give up the boxing bug.
这时候我真的很疲惫
We were really tired by this point.
你可以看到凯佐·拉威尔的动作很漂亮
You can see Pedro Love!! has some very good moves.
在他的拳击生涯当中 那时候他的状态大概正处于鼎盛时期
We're going here for probably the most blatant bout in the history of boxing.
他出手非常狠
We just wanted to make sure that it sold.
正中胸部 头部 现在
And again, right under Jesus, the hit.
在一开始 你第一次看到
And now, the beginning. This is the first time you see
生活对洛奇来说只是付钱的
what lies beneath the surface of Rocky
他一旦被触发
is this penchant for violence and energy and explosiveness and rage
就充满了暴力 力量和愤怒
when his button is pushed.
他可以变得非常强大
And then he can revert back to being quite docile.
我对这种潜力非常着迷
I was just fascinated with that pendulum, that swing,
一个普通人
where you can take a creature of nature
能爆发出如此不可思议的力量
and it can be the most docile-looking thing you can imagine,
但必须是在受到刺激的情况下
but if provoked,
才会产生这种非凡的自卫能力
it has extraordinary ability to defend itself
以求生存
and survive.
接下来是六回合的轻量级拳赛
Next a six-rounder between local lightweights Kid Brooks
布鲁克小子与甜蜜强森
and Sugar Johnson.
观众们的呐喊声 我们没有多少资金
All these voices in the crowd here, we didn't have much money,
所以基本上是剧组人员
so it's basically us.
我自己也参与其中
It's myself hassling myself, heckling myself.
你可以看到我和一位朋友的对话
That's Ray Sharkey's voice. He's a deceased actor and a friend of mine
我问：“有香烟吗？" “有 给你”
who said, "Lend me the smoke.'' We show it here.
你打得很烂 知道吗？真的很烂
WOMAN: You're a bum, you know that? You're a bum!
这里不是很多人能看懂 但是我相信
Not many people pick up on this, but I believe in a kind of situation where...
这种情况…
Let me see,
我想找一个合适的词来形容
I'm trying to find the right word.
这是…
Where it's..
人生当中的一个阶段 他们做的一件事
A certain aspect of one's life, a certain thing that they do,
是一个方向…
it's an orientation towards disco very
他发挥出自己的潜力
where he has set himself up to be discovered,
让自己变成了后来的意大利种马
little do we know, by just that name on the back of his robe, The Italian Stallion.
如果他没有这么做
If he didn't have that name,
就不会被阿波罗·克里德选中
he wouldn't have been picked out of the book by Apollo Creed.
他的事业也不会有起色
And his career wouldn't have taken off
实际上这是他在做选择
The mere fact that he had that as a nickname
到底是要默默无闻 还是崭露头角
was the difference between obscurity and getting discovered.
- 我什么时候再出赛？   - 大概两周后
-When do I fight again? -GAZZO: Maybe two weeks.
打电话给我 医生二十分钟内就会到了
Give me a call. The doctor should be in in about 20 minutes.
所以那时候你会发现 他处于人生的低谷
At that point you realize that he's really at rock bottom.
参加那样的比赛
Anyone who'd take that kind of beating
赢得了40美元
and end up with$40
还问：“我什么时候再出赛”
and then say, "When do I do it again,''
他应该是处于人生最低潮的时期
is pretty well at the very lowest echelon of his life.
我走到了宠物店门前
I wanted to write a pet shop into this
因为我觉得在这个萧瑟的街区
because I felt that in this bleak neighborhood
有一家宠物店 里面的小动物
the odd thing is to have a pet shop, where you have all these young creatures
在等待着新生活的开始
looking for a new beginning, a new life.
而这个老街区所有的人和物
And yet all the older creatures, the people that inhabit that neighborhood,
都已经经历过了盛年
are pretty well past their prime.
这个街区看起来死气沉沉的
It just seemed an interesting dichotomy.
我从这样的一座建筑前穿过街道
Especially across the street from a house of pain like this.
(SINGING)Take you back
Doo-doo doo doo
我们只在费城拍摄五天
STALLONE: We only had about five days to film in Philadelphia.
所以我们尽量抓紧时间
So we would really attack these scenes quickly
没有太多的出错空间
and there wouldn't be much room for mistakes.
我们力求完善
Or perfection, I might add.
这是我哥哥的演唱团
So this is my brother's singing group right here,
他们在新泽西州演出 愿意义务帮忙
who actually performed in New Jersey, would do this for free.
几位当地姑娘愿意担任临时演员
And then some of the girls, just locals standing around.
站在这里不动
I'd say, "You wanna be in this? Just stand here and don't move.''
那就是我哥哥
That's my brother right there.
我觉得这一幕的作用
And it just served, I guess, a little street-corner color.
让洛奇经过这群街头演唱者
And about how these guys, Rocky walks by,
你会一年比一年进步
you know, "You get better every year.''
暗示着费什镇一切都没有什么变化
Kind of intimating that nothing really changes in Fishtown.
这里的名字叫“费什镇”
That's what this neighborhood is called, Fishtown.
MEN:(SINGING)Doo-doo doo doo
Well, you put me down
Doo-doo doo doo
You put me down real nice
This love affair
我们最近重游了这一区 因为我要拍摄《洛奇》系列的
STALLONE: We recently revisited this neighborhood because I'm doing Rocky Balboa,
最后一集《洛奇·巴尔博》
which is the last of the Rocky series.
当你回到这里
And it's extraordinary how when you go back
看到这里的街道那么狭小 是一种很奇妙的感觉
and you see how tiny those streets are.
我觉得可能是我经历了太多的事
I guess that means either you become more experienced or whatever,
或者是那里真的太残旧
or too worldly.
回想一切看起来都那么小
Because everything looks smaller in retrospect.
我觉得这很有趣
This is something that I thought was really interesting.
不是随便安排的
And I don't know if anyone had picked up on it,
他的房间布局就是这样
just the way his house is set up.
一切都很古老 陈旧的留声机
Everything is archaic, the record player..
屋顶上有种装置
Yet, he uses an instrument there at the top,
用来挂衣服
which you're supposed to thy your laundry on
他用来夹住他的沙袋
and he uses that to clip his 45s on.
他将一张旧地毯挂在墙上
He has a mattress against the wall he uses for a heavy bag.
还有一盏破旧的吊灯
A bayonet, a machete on one side.
下面是他的两只小乌龟
Beneath it, two turtles,
这的确代表了他自己
which really represents pretty much him.
在外面人们觉得
Hard on the outside, at least what people look like.
洛奇的拳击手套就像他的盔甲
Rocky's leather, his hat, his gloves. It's like his armor.
但是他的内心
But inside
非常令人吃惊 是很柔软的
quite impressionable, pliable.
在这里…
This was kind of a...
我们要做一个决定
I had to make a choice here.
到底是通过洛奇·巴尔博 与洛奇·马西安诺对决的照片挂在墙上
Whether to actually delve into the world of reality by putting up Rocky Balboa
展现出现实世界
against a picture of Rocky Marciano.
但是我们如果这样做的话
It's like, "Okay. Now we're crossing the line here.
觉得有点过火了
"Saying that Rocky exists on the same plane as Rocky Marciano.''
我们没有采纳 所以制造出一些朦胧感
And we got away with it, so we were starting to blur the lines a little bit
让现实与幻想交界
between fantasy and reality.
这是我真实生活当中的照片
These are actual photos from my life.
跳马比赛 打橄榄球
Broad jumping contests and football,
还有在我家厨房拍的等等
when I was born in Hell's Kitchen and so on.
还有挂窗帘的那个把手
Again, the weapons, the knives, brass knuckles, bayonets
他用来当作…
that he uses
衣帽架
as coat racks and hat racks.
小学三年级的照片
My third-grade picture.
看到这张照片的时候 才发现这个男人变化
He looks at that and he realizes, "Man, where did it all go?
从一张天真无邪的脸 变成了一张伤痕累累
"I've gone from this innocent face to this beat up mug of donuts here.
肿得像面包一样的脸
"Big bag of donuts going nowhere.''
这间公寓是真的
This apartment was the real deal.
我们没有做任何改装
We didn't do a thing to it other than inhabit it
除了增添一些东西
and, of course, put a few of our things in here.
里面的灰尘和床的破旧程度 都是原来的样子
But the actual dirt, the broken-down quality of it, the bed,
这就是我刚到纽约的时候 住的那种屋子
this is pretty much the way my room was when I started out in New York City
在1969、1970年的时候
in 1969, 1970.
我们发现了这间公寓非常类似
And we found the place was very similar to it.
实际上这间公寓比我住的那间还稍微大点
Actually, this place is a little larger than the one I was in,
但我希望能表现出那种真实感
but I wanted to capture that, "This is it.
这就是他在地球上唯一存在的
"This is his last little corner on the planet,
最后一个小角落
"the only thing he exists in.
他拥有的唯一一间房子
"The only real estate that he has any domain over.''
塔莉娅·夏尔 是饰演这个角色的最佳人选
Talia Shire was a brilliant choice for this role.
她全情投入这个角色当中
She just inhabits this character without missing a beat.
这个姑娘是洛奇喜欢的类型
And it's the kind of girl that Rocky would be attracted to.
因为他并不…
Because he's not...
他从来不会喜欢漂亮女人
He never was... I never saw the character being attracted to glamorous types.
他寻找一个愿意听他倾诉
He looks for people that are willing to listen to him
不会评判他的人
and not be judgmental about him.
因为他有点不自信
'Cause, you know, he has certain insecurities himself,
所以他一直在寻找那种腼腆的类型
so he always looked for the shy type.
他做的一切似乎都不尽人意
Everything that was kind of like rejected by nature
从来没有成功过
or not successful
他的个性
in being well-rounded personalities.
致使他喜欢那种类型的姑娘
He seemed to be attracted to those types.
因为他就是那种类型 希望女孩子喜欢自己
'Cause he was that type. Like goes to like.
我们没有钱请一只明星狗
We didn't have money for a movie dog,
我有一只大狗 我不知道为什么
so I had a dog, a very large dog, I don't know why,
我们就让这个
at the time and we just threw him there.
150磅重的大家伙当一回临时演员
You know, a 150-pound bull mastiff which has no continuity whatsoever
有时候明星狗演出的效果也许会不自然
but, you know, sometimes the best laid plans are not the best.
而这个办法很成功
And it sort of worked.
在影片当中 出现了一只锁在笼子里的大狗
So in the middle of the story you have a giant dog in a cage
而其他的全都是玩偶 并没有人质疑
where everything else is a puppy. And no one questions it.
洛奇 你还没付钱
You gotta pay for that turtle food, rock head.
葛洛莉 你知道黑社会不用付钱
Hey, crime don't pay. You know that, Gloria.
那个黑暗的时代 逐渐在费城消失了
These are the real dock areas that are slowly disappearing in Philadelphia.
现在的治安好多了
And now condos are coming up.
在1975、1976年 这是真的
But in '75, '76 this was the real deal.
我觉得…
And I thought,
这是洛奇真正表现的时候
this is where Rocky really performs.
这是他最有信心的时刻
This is where he is the most comfortable.
在拳击场上他只是个孩子
He's a complete child of the streets.
而在这里
And here he is,
像我说的那样 他很有自信
like I said, fully at ease.
他非常凶悍
And extremely intimidating.
你想跑到哪里去？
Where are you going? Where you running?
这可能是…我想应该是 我们拍摄的第一幕
This is probably the first... I think this is the first scene.
不 应该是第二幕
First or second. No, the second scene we filmed.
我那时并不确定自己是否能出演这部电影
And I wasn't sure if! was gonna be on with this film.
我不确定能否将这部电影演完
I didn't know if! was gonna be able to complete the film.
我当时在拍另一部影片 很多人不确定
Because I was a novice and a lot of people were not sure
我是否能拍完整部影片
if I should stick around for the whole shoot.
所以这一幕决定了…
So this is the scene that really would determine
我是否会完成整部电影
whether I would complete the film.
即使我知道制片人和剧组人员都很努力
Even though I know the producers were on board and everyone was on board,
影片的拍摄有一定的约束 如果当时他们不喜欢我的表演
there were certain stipulations that if they didn't like the acting
或者是我所表达出的那种感觉
or the message that I was conveying at that point,
我就会被换掉 这我理解
I would be replaced. And I understood that.
所以这一幕…
So, anyway, this scene here
可以说展现了主角的个性
kind of like really set the tone for who Balboa is.
两分钟内他从威胁说要打断那人的拇指
In two minutes he goes from being a man who's ready to break your thumbs
转变到给他提建议
to giving advice
知道他会惹祸上身
and knowing that he's gonna get in trouble for this.
他是在自寻烦恼
He's really setting himself up
帮这个人打掩护
to take the fall for this other fellow.
在这里我想说
Oh, here's a little tidbit.
这顶帽子本身…
The hat itself is...
当我参与拍摄的时候 我们并没有资金购买服装
When I went there, we really didn't have any money for a wardrobe.
所以你看到的一切基本上是大家一起凑来的
So everything you see pretty much is what the people threw together themselves.
我没有帽子
And I didn't have a hat.
我心想：天啊 这个角色的个性独特
And I thought, "Boy, there's something about this thing, this character.
他需要一套合适的装扮
"He needs a complete suit of armor or something.''
我找到了一家快要倒闭的二手商店 看到了这顶帽子
So, I found this broken-down second-hand store and this hat.
他们说：“不 不 你不能戴这顶帽子”
And they said, "Oh, no, no. You can't wear that hat.''
我问：“为什么？"
I said, "Why?''
其中一位制片人说
One of the execs said,
“因为他没有必要戴着一顶帽子”
"Because Gene Hackman wore a hat in French Connection.!!
我说 “这是否意味着永远不允许戴帽子？"
I said, "Well, does that mean hats are off limits forever?
“因为我看到别的电影里有人戴帽子”
"Cause one fellow wears a hat?''
他说 “你不希望被控告侵权吧？"
And he goes, "Well, you don't want to be accused of copying him.''
我说 “我觉得这个角色与众不同”
I said, "I think this character is quite different than Popeye Doyle.''
所以我们一直为这件事争论不休
It was an on-going battle, believe it or not.
我说 “我真的想戴那顶帽子 拜托了 让我一次 好吗？"
So finally I said, "I really want to wear the hat. Please, spare me this, okay?''
我真的相信那顶帽子
And I truly believe that, that hat
衬托出了整个角色
really set off the whole character.
看起来很自然
It's just something that, it seems to work.
很能够突显个性 就像查理·卓别林
I know it sounds odd, but like Charlie Chaplin and his hat
戴着帽子 拿着拐杖
or Buster Keaton and his hat, there's something...
还有保罗·罗伊德
Or even Lloyd. Harold Lloyd and his hat.
有自己的个性装扮
There's something about this character and his whole outfit that speaks volumes.
你不照我的话做 我很没有面子
When you don't do what I tell you to do, you make me look bad.
这是乔治·费奈尔
This was Joe Spine!!.
我当临时演员的时候认识了他
I met Joe when I was an extra on Farewell, My Lovely.
我对他非常崇拜
And I always found him to be fascinating.
他是个十分独特的人
And kind of like a real unique one-off type.
超级疯狂
Completely insane.
独特 幽默 古怪 危险 他有许多特点
Unique, funny, irreverent, dangerous. He had a lot of things going for him.
所以当我有了这个机会 再次找他当临时演员
So, when I got the opportunity I said, "From one extra to another extra,
说 “我有一部电影 你愿意参与吗？"
"I got this little movie, you wanna be in it?''
他说 “当然”
He said, "Sure.''
不过他真的很出色
And here he is. But he was great.
非常出色 很擅长即兴表演
Really great. Excellent ad-libster.
有一名建筑工人告诉我
So here, from what I was told was... Actually a construction worker
他的性格很糟糕 在电影当中
who was terrible.. I mean a terrible personality in the movie,
而并非在现实生活中
a nice guy in reality.
我觉得这个工地是一个很棒的外景
This I thought was one of the great things that Bill Conti would do
在这里你可以看到他转头回来
around this time here, you'd see him go from "I should've broke your thumbs,''
听到比尔喊了几句话
then you hear Bill knock out a few notes here,
当你带回到…
which sort of brings you back
洛奇的苦恼当中 应该说是洛奇的孤独
into the pain of Rocky. I should say, the isolation of Rocky.
洛奇走路的时候 总是在打拳
Rocky walks, he's always jabbing, he's always hitting at something.
当时我要对战一名年轻的拳击手
There was a fighter that I was trying to channel at the time, a young fighter.
他总是一边走 一边抽动   一边轻弹他的衣领
And he's always moving and twitching and flipping up his collar
摩拳擦掌 发出嘶嘶的声音
and rolling his hands and making a hissing sound
好像在打拳一样
as though he's throwing punches.
其中有许多都是我的习惯
That's who I took a lot of my habits from.
当我看到一个场景的时候 我都会想：
This I thought was... When I see a scene, I go, "Okay, here's the scene.
我们该如何…
"How do we make it..
我们该怎样仅仅通过开柜子的动作来表现出人物的个性？
"How can we tell a lot about a character just from opening up a locker?''
我灵机一动：就从帽子里拿出一张纸条
And I thought, "Okay, fine, in his hat, which is a part of his uniform,
上面记着柜锁的密码
"he keeps his combination for the same locker that he's had for six years.
可他还是打不开锁
"He still can't remember the combination.''
这时候 多数人都会说
Then, most guys would go out and say,
“抱歉 我的柜锁坏了”
"Excuse me, something's wrong with my combination.''
而洛奇就直接把锁砸烂了
Rocky just acts impulsively and crash!
用灭火筒
Fire extinguisher.
门打开了
Voilà! New occupant.
手里还拿着灭火筒 我不知道
Still holding the fire extinguisher. Well, I don't know, I just...
我觉得这一幕很滑稽
This to me appeals to my sense of comedy where...
这不再是你的柜子了
It ain't your locker no more.
洛奇还是不明白
Rocky still can't figure it out.
什么？我六年来都是用这个柜子
What you talking about? It's been my locker...
他已经被开除了
That he's being had, that he's being shipped out.
在训练馆里 管理员说
In the gym life, instead of just saying,
“我们想借用你的柜子”
"Oh, you know what? We'd like to use your locker.''
某一天 你看到自己的包被挂起来 就意味着你被开除了
One day you're in a bag hanging on a hook. I mean, that's it. You're out.
他在哪里？
Where is he?
他和迪波在外面练习
He's outside working with Dipper.
- 他心情很糟   - 我也是
-He's in a bad mood. -So am I.
我第一次见到布吉斯·梅迪斯的时候 觉得有个角色…
First time you see Burgess Meredith. There was a character, I think,
让人感到难以打败
Howie Steindler who was a real hard-bitten gym-owner,
是洛杉矶一个传奇的拳击手
legendary in Los Angeles,
布吉斯表演得非常好 并且加入了自己的特色
and Burgess did an amazing imitation of him then added his own originality to it.
后面那位拳手是前世界冠军 莫德勒·拉莫
The guy behind, getting hit there, is Man do Ramos, former world champion,
我的朋友斯坦·肖
and a friend of mine Stan Shaw
饰演迪波
who's pounding away at him, playing Dipper.
你想干嘛？
Hell! What do you want?
还有一件有趣的事 就是这位训练馆的老板
It's kind of interesting that Rocky
这么多年来
is finally getting a little dose of honesty
终于对洛奇说了一回实话
from this ring owner, from this gym owner for all these years.
他终于对他说 “你是个整脚货”
He's finally just saying,
“你打起拳来活像猩猩”
"Look, you're a bum, everything you fight is a tomato can.
“你一生当中唯一特别的”
"You didn't break your nose. That's the only thing unique about you
“是你鼻子从未被打断”
"in your entire life, you don't have a broken nose.
“你真的应该考虑转行”
"Really, you should consider some other line of work.''
然后 他回答：“我打赢了史派德·里柯”
And then he comes back with, "Well, I beat Spider Rico.''
他说 “他是个蹩脚货”
He goes, "Come on, he's a bum.''
我所有的对手都是蹩脚货
You know, everyone I fight is a bum.
这两个人之间就像是父子关系
This is a real heavy duty father-son relationship.
只能说是敌对的父子
Or should I say, merely estranged father and son.
不管孩子怎么做 都不能令父亲满意
No matter what the child does, he can't appease this embittered old man
因为他的梦想破碎了
because his dreams have been shattered
他从来没有过一次漂亮的胜利
and he's not about to cut anybody some slack. No one.
从来都没有
No one any slack.
你也该看看我的表现
You should've seen me too.
嘿 孩子
Hey, kid.
有没有想过退休？
You ever think about retiring?
有没有想过退休
"Think about retiring?'' Yeah.
好了 暂停
All right, time.
- 你等一下   - 什么？
-Time! -What?
我喜欢你的柜子
I dig your locker, man.
实际上迪波这个角色…
Actually, that character, Dipper,
他后来胜利了
he was paid off later on.
这是两个最后被删除的镜头 其中之一
It's one of the two scenes that never made it to the final cut.
当洛奇回来
And that's when Rocky comes back
阿波罗·克里德开始在训练场骚扰洛奇
and Apollo Creed starts to harass him in the gym,
故意挑衅他 同时迪波
just shows up with a camera crew. In the middle of all that, that character,
也开始骚扰他 打了洛奇一拳
Stan Shaw, Dipper, starts harassing him, punches Rocky.
让他趴到地上亲他的脚
Says, "Get down there and kiss my feet...'' Whatever.
洛奇一拳将他打倒了
And Rocky just lays him out
这下阿波罗·克里德意识到
and in such a way that Apollo Creed realizes
他有可能选错了拳手
that maybe he might have picked on the wrong obscure fighter.
这一幕第一次拍摄的时候 我走进来 按照剧本进行表演
This is the scene where I went in and did it pretty much as scripted
到了第二次 我说 “咱们来即兴发挥一把吧”
and then the second time around, I said, "Let's ad-lib a little bit
增加一些眼神的交流
"and get some of these odd moments in there that...''
要不要帮你清理鸟笼？
You need some help?
我发现如果过于依赖剧本
I find that when you stick to the script too much,
在重拍四五次之后 就会变得…
after the fourth or fifth take, you know, it becomes...
会变得枯燥无味
Well, it becomes a little stale.
要是再增添一些即兴表演
And if you can just throw a few other lines in there,
会更有新鲜感
it sort of freshens it up.
我感触颇深
"Hard night.'' This and that.
尤其是当我开始对鸟说话的时候
Especially when I go over and I start talking to the birds.
都用六年了 我不难过
....locker for about six years. It don't bother me.
反正柜子很烂
Lockers are bad, anyway.
这里他再一次
Right here, this is, again, that man is pouring his heart out
向女孩倾诉 可她太害羞了 内心非常脆弱
to the girl, and she's so shy, so beat up emotionally inside
不知道该怎么回应他 所以洛奇不再继续骚扰她了
that she can't answer. So, rather than Rocky just continue to harass her,
开始对鸟说话 排解她的压力
he just talking to the birds to take the pressure off of her.
让她不再感觉到 他在打她的主意
So she doesn't feel as though he's badgering her.
后来他突然插了一句 “你要人送你回家吗？"
And then he'll slip in, "Oh, you need someone to walk you home? Okay.''
这是洛奇的惯用伎俩
That was one of my favorite shots.
用坏人来吓唬她
A lot of creeps like... You can always tell a creep.
当然 他本身就像个坏人 眼睛受了伤
Of course, he looks like the creep with the bleeding eye.
每条街上都有坏人
Every other block, there's a creep.
你应该会分辨坏人
You can always tell a creep. "You can always tell a creep.''
他又一次非常尴尬 他感到难堪
Now he's again really awkward, and he just feels quite awkward
所以走了
and leave.
待在笼子一整天也很难受
.you guys get up. I know you had a hard day in the cage.
我觉得透过笼子看 塔莉娅·夏尔的
I think Talia Shire just did a great job.
这个镜头很棒 她就像笼子里的小鸟
Through the cage, she is the bird in the cage.
飞不出去 真的很棒
Can't fly. It's great stuff
这个地方…是真的
This place here is for real.
而这里是用电脑合成的
And this is one of the technicians.
我需要有个醉汉倒在外面
I said, "You know what? I just need someone drunk outside.''
我觉得这表现出巴尔博的另一面
So, I think again it shows another side of Balboa,
他是一个好人 只不过外表有点吓人
that he just is a good guy. Rather than have a bum freeze outside,
他总是喜欢帮助别人
he'll just bring him inside, ask for no thanks. Nothing.
不求任何回报
The bum will never know that he probably saved him from frostbite.
洛奇 眼睛怎么了？
What's with the eye?
- 比赛中打的 - 希望你最后能赢
-Been fighting. -Hope you won it, at least.
我打的很好 你应该来看
Oh, yeah, did real good. You should've seen me.
轻量级世界冠军 阿波罗·克里德…
TV ANNOUNCER: heavyweight champion of the world Apollo Creed at Kennedy Airport...
他又一次提到了史派德·里柯
STALLONE: He then begins to speak about Spider Rico and oddly enough
有趣的是 在我们现在拍摄的电影 《洛奇·巴尔博》当中
in the Rocky Balboa film that we're doing now,
史派德·里柯在30年后又回来了
Spider Rico, 30 years later, is brought back.
你不会知道角色什么时候会再次出现
And so you never know when a character's going to re-emerge.
这一幕我们只拍了一遍
We had one take on this.
这非常值得一提
This is pretty remarkable.
那天已经很晚了 这间厕所就像剧本里写的一样
We were running late and this bathroom, the way it was written,
有点阴森恐怖 大家都觉得我在这里的表现不错
was supposed to be a little slice of hell. I must admit they did a great job there.
那些纸屑 墙上的名字 还有一面小镜子
Toilet paper, things, names on the wall and a little piece of mirror
波特·杨在梳洗
and Burt Young is trying to salvage
镜子里的影像… 他再照镜子也是徒劳
some visual on that mirror. He's just vainly looking in there
我不知道他为什么要梳头发
and I don't know why he's combing his hair.
我觉得这个角色
It's just a little oddity that I think
性格有点古怪
characters that are interesting have.
他宁愿弯下腰 照那一小块镜子
That he would rather bend over and look into a little sliver of a mirror.
我不知道他在干什么 他又没有女朋友
I don't know what he's doing. He has no date.
这一切都停留在同一个角度 没有被删减过
And everything stays in the same angle without a cut.
你也好不到哪里去
? . . no crowd around you neither.
我想杀了那个打破镜子的白痴
I'd like to kill the freaking moron who broke the mirror.
我们离开这个臭地方 好吗？
Come on. Let's get out of this stink.
我想和你谈谈
I wanna talk to you anyway.
波特·杨在这里的表现也很出色
Burt Young was also absolutely brilliant in this.
我觉得这个角色已经没有什么需要补充的了
There's nothing I would say you'd have to add to this character.
在那一幕当中
In that one little scene he sort of set the tone
已经将他的特点完全展现 他走路的样子
for who he is, the way he walks..
就好像背上背了什么东西似的
As though the world has dropped a boulder on his back.
我妹妹 她再没人追就要枯萎了
My sister. If she don't start living, her body's gonna dry up.
他总是控制别人 总是想离开…
Always manipulating, always wanting to get out of that...
他在一家肉店工作
He works in a meat house.
当然好 给我啤酒
Sure. Beer.
想方设法离开肉店 无论付出什么代价
Anything to get out of the meat house. No matter what it takes.
所以他总是强迫洛奇做一些事 他想当一名拳击手
So, he's always hustling Rocky for something. He wants to be a collector.
他觉得像洛奇一样 当一名拳击手
He thinks that being a collector, like Rocky,
是事业的长久之计
for a loan shark, is a glamorous career move.
你提到二百周年国庆的比赛？
You're speaking now of your much-publicized Bicentennial fight.
这将是史上最伟大的运动盛事
Right. This is gonna be the greatest sporting event in the country's...
卡尔饰演的
Carl Weathers,
阿波罗·克里德 我是说他的确…
in as Apollo Creed, he really had
喜欢耍态度 而且有点狂妄自大
a great attitude and a certain kind of swagger
恰恰体现了阿波罗·克里德的
and voice that embodied what we were looking for
角色个性
in the character of Apollo Creed.
没有人能比他演得更好 他的身材 他的嗓音
No one could have done it better. I mean, he had the body, he had the voice,
他的态度 都非常适合
he had the attitude. He was really great.
他是个喜剧演员
The bartender is Don Sherman. He's a comedian
同样也在30年后的 《洛奇·巴尔博》当中出现
who also appears in Rocky Balboa 30 years later.
他有些特点是非常好的
But there's something about him, that's just great, and he is...
他是在传统学校读书的人
You know he's a guy that's old school, little bit of a racist,
洛奇似乎拥有阿波罗·克里德的才华
and it shows that Rocky is like, in awe of Apollo Creed's talent.
只不过…
And just...
他是个好人 不喜欢别人说坏话…
You know, a good guy who doesn't like other people bad-mouthing
反对种族歧视
or suggesting that someone is different because of race, creed or color.
所以他离开了
So, he just moves on.
你有什么好气的？
Why you getting so insulted?
要我努力？好
You want me to take a shot? All right.
我就喝一杯
I'll take a shot.
这是我们第一次使用 手托式摄影机拍摄的
This is one of the first uses of the Steadicam right here.
当时那是一种很少用的工具
At that time it was a unwieldy piece of equipment
你可以听到背景当中有摩擦的杂音
that you could hear the grinding sound. And there'd be bolts and washers
周围有嘈杂的声音
attached to the side,
是盖尔·布朗想出来的 保持平衡的办法
by Garrett Brown who in vented it, to keep the balance.
这里都是用手托式摄影机拍摄的
So, here it is in all its glory. Really came in handy.
去你的 笨蛋
-Get lost, creep. -Screw you, yo-yo!
是这些家伙教你那样说话的？
These guys teach you to talk like that?
其实这是非常重要的一幕
This actually is a very, very important scene.
乔蒂·莱提西亚饰演的这个小姑娘 他父亲与我们家有交情
That little girl is played by Jodi Letizia whose father was friend of the family.
我们的资金太少 忘记把背景当中的拖车移走了
And we were so broke, we forgot to move the Hertz truck in the background,
那辆工具车 我们利用周围的一切
the equipment truck. We just grabbed what we could there
因为只有五天时间拍摄
because we had five days.
话说回来 这女孩长得还不赖
Anyway, this girl with the dirty mouth wasn't bad looking,
可是没有男生瞧得起她
but none of the guys ever took her serious.
他们从不约她出去
They never took her out for any serious date.
- 为什么？  - 男生就是这样
-Why? -'Cause that's the way guys are.
那些从楼房里透出来的灯光
You can see flares from the lights on buildings. We just put up one big light.
就像监狱里那样昏暗
It looks like a prison break, but..
我们希望这一幕当中表现出的情感
We were hoping that the emotion in this scene would
能够掩盖照明的缺陷
override the fact that it was not exactly lit properly.
以及你听到的
Or that you would hear the whirring sound,
手托式摄影机发出的摩擦声
the grinding sound of the actual Steadicam in this scene.
回到这一幕本身
Anyway, getting back to the scene itself,
把技术问题放在一边
mechanics aside,
洛奇其实在说他自己
it's really Rocky talking about himself.
他认为名声是很重要的
Talking about, "You really are a victim of your reputation.''
是世界上最脆弱的
That the most fragile thing in the world is your reputation.
一旦遭到破坏就很难再弥补
Once it's broken, once it's cracked, it's really hard to put it back together again.
你觉得自己为什么没有男朋友？
Why don't you think you have a boyfriend?
也许仅仅是你跟坏人交往
And you can have a reputation shattered
就能破坏你的名声
just by associating with the wrong people.
你不必做任何事
You don't even have to do anything.
别人就会认为你是其中一员
People automatically assume you're one of them.
懂不懂？
? . .nice friends. You understand?
与聪明人交往就会…
You hang out with smart people...
在这一切之后
And after all this...
与混混交往就会有混混的朋友
You hang out with yo-yo people...
你会觉得他…
? you would think that he would..
是想令别人觉悟 想把自己的经验
He's trying to touch somebody, literally trying to give his experience over
告诉这个小姑娘 最后他以为自己成功的时候
to this one little girl. In the end he thinks he's accomplished something.
他一整天一直在遭到拒绝
Remember it's been a long day of rejection?
再一次惨遭拒绝
Well, one more bitter rejection.
去你的 变态
Screw you, creep-o!
我喜欢这个角色的一点就是…
And what I like about the character is that he agrees.
他也赞同 他算什么？ 凭什么给别人忠告？
Who is he to give advice, rather than take an exception?
对 你凭什么给人忠告 你只是个变态
Yeah, who are you to give advice, creep-o?
你算老几？
Who are you?
又在练习他的拳法
Still practicing his boxing.
虽然失败了 他仍然充满幻想
And though he's well past it, he still has the illusions.
“二百周年大赛”
我很早就想到了这个主意 就是命中注定
This is what I was talking about earlier on, about this idea of predisposition.
他起的这个绰号“意大利种马”
The fact that he had the name "Italian Stallion'' on his bathrobe
是当地人人皆知的
and was known locally as the "Italian Stallion''
他的技术非常高超
totally comes in handy.
在200周年诞国庆纪念日
'Cause when he's looking for an opponent to fight
他想找一位对手比试 本应由哥伦比亚公司讨论
on the country's birthday, supposedly discovered by Columbus,
他的对手是谁 不过阿波罗说
who else to fight but, well, one of his fellow countrymen,
要找一个跟他来自同一个国家的对手
as Apollo says?
我很相信命运 就像当所有的演员和编剧…
I'm a big believer in predisposition. It's like when all these actors and writers
觉得不会有结果的时候
feel as though they're not getting anywhere,
我告诉他们要继续坚持 因为你不知道结果如何
I tell them, "Keep going out, keep going out.'' 'Cause you never know.
只要遇到合适的时机
You just happen to be at the right place atone time,
也许一年之后 你会被别人记起
and maybe a year later, you'll remember it.
有人突然某天会想起你
Something clicks in another person's mind, they recall you being in there.
接下来
And the next thing you know,
你的命运可能会因此改变
your fortunes are changed.
而不是坐在那里 等待机会上门
As opposed to sitting around, waiting for opportunities to knock on the door.
…所以找藉口避免被我修理
.don't have to be the chump who gets whipped.
我只能说我是个好的主办者
All I can say is I'm a good promoter.
我在世界各国主办无数拳赛
I've promoted fights...
他是一位资深的主办者
This is a really old-school promoter.
我在这场拳赛阴沟里翻船
.and I've broken my ass over this one.
我们现在已经没有这样的主办者了
They really don't have promoters like this anymore.
但我已黔驴技穷
I don't know what else to do!
我们没有足够的资金 所以利用了制片人的这间办公室
Again, we didn't have much money, so this is a producer's office.
我们设置了窗外的背景
And we just threw up a background there
让这里看起来像费城
to make it look like it's in Philadelphia.
所以阿波罗·克里德在元旦当天…
So, Apollo Creed, on January 1st,
给当地毫无胜算的人一个机会
gives a local underdog fighter an opportunity.
一个名不见经传的小子
A snow-white underdog...
我说过这部电影的预算很紧
When I tell you this film was done on a shoestring, actually it was...
我们必须节约开支
Shoestring is a little too opulent.
非常节省
It's like done on a shoe nail.
我们拍了28天
This thing was done in about 28 days.
在这个国家的国庆日 让当地男孩有机会出赛
? . .give a local Philadelphia boy a shot at the greatest title in the world.
经费不足100万美元
Was a bit under$1 million.
这就是我的看法
Now that's the way I see it
而且就要如此进行
and that's the way it's gonna be.
阿波罗 我喜欢
Apollo, I like it.
有美国的味道
It's very American.
不 杰更斯 这非常聪明
No, Jergens. It's very smart.
卡尔的表演非常出色
Carl Weathers really brought a lot to this in the way of...
他的嗓音 态度 机智 都很符合这个角色
With his voice and his attitude and sense of intelligence of the character.
我们回到了洛奇住的街区
A gain we're back in Rocky's neighborhood.
这个下雪的场面很完美
The snow is perfect, cold weather.
非常符合当时的情景
The grayness, it just speaks volumes.
- 怎么了？   - 我只是要确认一下
-GAZZO: What is it? -I wanna check this thing out.
洛奇在练习他的速记能力
Rocky just struggles with his bookkeeping techniques there, you know.
我喜欢乔·斯皮内尔 在这里增添他自己的表演
And this is what I like about Joe Spine!!. It's where he'll add little things here.
我是说
I mean, he goes like,
我会听到一些高频噪音
"You don't think I hear things? Lot of canaries flying around the docks.''
我们除了一起表演这场戏之外
We just threw this scene together.
每天只有打招呼和道别
Pretty much it was just, "Here, you have a date tonight. Goodbye.''
仅此而已 不过对这里的 对手戏很有帮助
And that was it, but we started to add all this here.
我觉得…你应该表现出那种嫉妒
I felt that you should have the outside world of jealousy.
这个家伙对巴尔博感到嫉妒
This fellow here is jealous of Balboa
不断的顶撞他
and just has to continually run down whatever he has in life,
嫉妒他有女朋友 句句针对他
like calling his girlfriend mentally challenged.
他老是心情不好 你应该多积点口德
He's always in a bad mood. You ought to count your blessings.
趁你现在还很健康
You're still a healthy person.
有一次排演的时候 洛奇冲到了车里
At one time, believe it or not, Rocky gets in the car
他说 “你们俩不如来个了断”
and he goes, "Why don't you two guys just settle it once and for all?''
然后他开始开车
And the loan shark starts to drive
我们俩在后面干了起来
and myself and the driver get in the back seat and have it out.
我是说我们在车后座大打出手
I mean, have a major-league fistfight in the back of that car.
幸亏我恢复了理智 我们把那一幕删除了
Fortunately, I came to my senses and re-wrote that scene.
你怎会知道她的名字？
How'd you know her name?
你以为我不知道吗？
You don't think I hear things?
- 洛奇   - 什么？
-BUDDY: Hey, Rock. -What?
- 记住我说的话   - 什么话？
-Remember what I told you? -What'd you tell me?
带她去动物园
Take her to the zoo.
你个王八蛋！
Come on out of the car!
- 还要咖啡吗 克里德先生？   - 不了 谢谢
-Some more coffee, Mr. Creed? -No, thanks, Shirley.
这里就是…
And he re it is.
最后一个…
This is the final...
比克查·史密斯呢？
How about Big Chuck Smith?
可以说是我刚才所说的 最后一个例子
You might say, the final example of what I was saying earlier on
关于命运的
about predisposition.
这个名字突然出现在他的面前
The fact that the name comes in handy.
阿波罗 你到底要找什么？
Exactly what are you looking for, Apollo?
这才是我要找的
This is what I'm looking for.
意大利种马
The Italian Stallion.
就是这里
There it is.
他自己选中了洛奇·巴尔博 否则我今天也不会坐在这里
If he had just called himself Rocky Balboa, I wouldn't be sitting here today.
听着 是绰号 意大利种马
The Italian Stallion.
媒体会极感兴趣的
The media will eat it up.
是谁发现美洲大陆的？ 意大利人 对不对？
Who discovered America? An Italian, right?
还有什么比与意大利后裔赛拳更棒的？
What would be better than to get it on with one of his descendants?
他是个左撇子
He's a southpaw.
我不要你和左撇子比赛
I don't want you messing around with southpaws.
- 他们的拳路是相反的   - 没什么大不了的
-They do everything backwards. -Southpaw nothing.
我会在三回合内撂倒他
Ill drop him in three.
阿波罗·克里德出战意大利种马
Apollo Creed meets the Italian Stallion.
听起来好像怪兽电影
Sounds like a damn monster movie.
的确听起来像怪兽电影
It does sound like a monster movie.
我以前很会玩棍球
I used to be deadly at stickball.
- 你确定她知道我要来？  - 她非常兴奋
-Your sister knows I'm coming? -PAU LIE: She's very excited.
看看这些肿起来的手和关节
-Look at these swollen hands. -Yeah.
这个角色…
This is character.
保利在慢慢地引我上钩
Paulie is just slowly setting me up.
洛奇还不知道自己已经入了局
Rocky is unaware that he's being kind of led into
保利耍了一个小阴谋
this pretty superficial scheme by Paulie to kind of like bring him into the fold.
让洛奇帮他一个大忙
To make Rocky do him a big favor
让他跟他妹妹约会
by having him date his sister.
他安排了这一切
Setting the whole thing up.
当然 他妹妹并不知道这是他的主意
Of course, his sister had no idea that this was happening.
- 给我根火柴   - 去找他 算是帮我一个忙
Go to him for me. As a favor.
上次我吃火鸡是三年前 只卖两块钱的特价货
Yeah, yeah. Last time I had a turkey was when they had a two-dollar special.
很多人认为洛奇很会抽烟
Now, a lot of people thought that, that was Rocky smoking a joint.
不是的
我练习了很多次 总是扭动香烟的根部
I would just get cold sometimes and just keep twisting the end of the cigarette
才达到这个效果
until it looked that way.
- 你妹妹知道我要来？   - 对 她很兴奋
-Your sister knows I'm coming? -Yeah, yeah. She's very excited.
这里 在费什镇
Here we are in Fishtown.
我觉得这些角色 波特·杨和我
And I think these characters really... Burt Young and I...
我喜欢他们走路的样子
I like them when they were moving.
他们一直在走 但不知道要去哪里
They're always moving but they're going nowhere.
上上下下 到处游荡 不知道要去哪里
Up and down and around and always traveling, going nowhere.
保利 你回来晚了
ADRIAN: Paulie, you're late.
你打给医院了？
You call the hospital?
我晚归她就会打电话问医院
She calls the hospital if I'm ten minutes late.
这是费什镇的一个真实的房间
This house is an actual house in Fishtown.
我觉得看上去
And I think it kind of, like,
非常拥挤 非常狭窄
jams together how cloistered
很有压迫感 她和保利的生活
and how pressured her life and Paulie's life are.
根本没有延伸的空间
There is no room for expansion.
看起来很有逼迫感
And it's just like a pressure cooker.
他当然感到难堪 因为他觉得妹妹总是会听他的话
Of course, he's embarrassed 'cause he figured his sister always listened to him.
可她现在竟然敢自作主张
Now she dares have her own opinion.
因为她知道哥哥在利用她
'Cause she's mortified that her brother would use her as sort of a bargaining chip.
保利 我不能去
ADRIAN: I can't go!
别跟我耍脾气
Don't get wise with me now.
我已经厌烦你永远是个输家
I'm tired of you being a loser.
保利 不要那么说我！
ADRIAN: Don't call me that, Paulie!
这是…
This is
一种人物个性的展现
exposition, exposition, exposition.
你怎么没告诉我他会来？
ADRIAN: Why didn't you tell me you were bringing him home?
- 我怎么没告诉你？   - 我不去 保利！
PAULIE: How do you know I didn't?
我也能感觉到气氛的尴尬
I remember him feeling, the character feeling really, really uncomfortable.
他没有想到会发生这样的事
There's all this kind of like violence happening at the other end of the hall.
以为可以来享用一顿美味的感恩节晚餐
He thought he was coming over for a nice Thanksgiving dinner,
现在他觉得自己被迫跟一个
and he's now literally being forced to go out on a date
不情愿跟自己在一起的人约会
with someone who doesn't want to.
我觉得波特在这里的表演
And here... I think the way Burt did this,
完全展现出了他的个性
this really says it all about his personality.
在感恩节 艾德丽安花了一整天
On Thanksgiving he'll take something she's been working on all day
烤好的火鸡 被他扔出了门外
and heave it into the alley.
我们的预算只够买一只鸡
A little footnote. We only had a budget for one chicken,
或者是一只小火鸡
sort of a small turkey.
外面有个人披着毛毯
So there's a man out there with a blanket
抓每次飞出去的那些鸟
catching the bird every time it flew out.
那一幕他们拍了6次 结果火鸡烤好的时候
So, they did that shot about six times and by the time that turkey was done,
可以说肉质还蛮柔软的
you might say it was pretty tender.
继续说 说些笑话给她听
Forget nothing. Go ahead. Tell her something funny.
这一幕很有趣
I think Burt is really great in this scene.
他一直用手指戳我
The way he just keeps needling me with his fingers.
不断逼迫我
He's just jabbing me, prodding me, pushing me.
就像一个流氓 逼我走过去
See, the way he just, like a giant rake pulling me down the hall there.
我不知道该说什么
I don't know what to say.
快去
Funny.
洛奇每次紧张的时候都会挥动拳头
Rocky, every time he gets nervous, he just keeps twitching and throwing punches
这是他的肢体语言
and it's the only way he knows how to converse, with body language.
艾德丽安 是我 洛奇
Yo, Adrian. It's me, Rocky.
洛奇 知道吗？
Rocky, you know?
听着…
Listen...
我觉得重要的是…
Here I thought it was important
他感觉非常别扭
that he feels so in credibly uncomfortable
而且很愚蠢
but also so stupid.
就好像：拜托 这很荒唐
I mean, he's like, "Come on. This is ridiculous.''
我才没有 我活像个白痴
I ain't doing fine. I look like an idiot.
很多想约女孩子的人…
As much as he wants to date the girl,
都会觉得这样很尴尬
it's like hell. You couldn't put him in a more uncomfortable situation.
我觉得这一幕的拍摄非常好 很真实
And I thought the way it was shot was very good. It was like no frills.
没有特写镜头 非常直白
No great close-ups. Just jam right into it
让这种尴尬的气氛 自然的展现出来
and let the uncomfortable framing and situation speak for itself.
或许我们…
So, how about maybe you and I
一起出去吃个饭
go out together, get something to eat.
我不知道 或许分享一些欢笑
Maybe laugh a little bit. Who knows, you know?
你想不想…
Would you like to...
你想不想和我一起出去？
Would you like to, maybe, you and me go out together?
你愿意吗？
What do you think? Would you like to?
她突然把门打开了
And then she opens the door and almost flattens him.
他以为她已经拒绝了他 所以躲在屋子里不肯出来
She's already dressed and ready. So she's had an epiphany in the room,
然而她觉得很无聊
something which is rather pretty bold.
连洛奇也不敢相信她会改变主意
Even Rocky can't believe it. She's had a change of heart.
她做出了决定
This is, she's hit that crossroad, period.
她看着镜子
When she looks in the mirror,
眼睛却膘到别的地方
it's as though she's says, "All right. I've been going on one way
心里想着要做一件出人意料的事
"and I'm not the same person, I got to do something drastic.
她无法再忍受她的哥哥 不能再忍受这样的生活
"I cannot take my brother anymore, I can't take this life anymore.
就跟他约会看看会怎么样吧
"Let's just see what happens.''
- 她喜欢做些什么？   - 溜冰
-What's your sister like to do? -Ice-skate.
这是影片当中我最喜欢的一段对白
Here's one of my favorite lines in the movie,
总结了…
which kind of summarizes
洛奇的生活变得很模糊
how Rocky's life has become one big blur.
你知道吗？反正我也不想吃火鸡
Listen, I don't want no turkey anyway, you know?
但今天是感恩节
But it was Thanksgiving.
是什么？
What?
- 感恩节   - 那是对你
-It was Thanksgiving. -Yeah, to you.
对我来说则是星期四
But to me it's Thursday, right?
是啊 对我来说只不过是星期四
Yeah, "To me it was just Thursday.''
他没有等她就先走了
He's trying to do manners, but he doesn't wait for her.
这一切都很自然
All this stuff it was just flowing.
他一点也不做作
It wasn't as though, "So, you walk.''
没有说 “让我过去”
It wasn't like, "Okay. Let me walk through.''
这很奇怪 他以前从没约会过
It was just weird. He's never really been out on a date before.
感觉很特别
And it's just odd.
我们就顺其自然了
And we just let that work.
- 似乎很安静   - 我想是打烽了
-It looks kind of quiet. -I think it's closed.
原本这部影片里应该有200个临时演员
Originally this was written for 200 extras.
圣诞节和新年之际 在外面的街道上
Outside, New Years, I mean, Christmas. This was gonna be like...
对 原来的剧本里写的是圣诞节 而不是感恩节
I'm sony. Yeah, it was around Christmas. It wasn't Thanksgiving at the time.
布鲁斯说我们有个小麻烦
And the producer said, "We have a slight problem.''
我问 “怎么了？" 他说 “我们资金不够 可否改一下？"
I said, "What's that?'' "We have no money, can we change it''?
我问 “有几名临时演员？" 他说 “一名”
I said, "A II right. How many extras can I have?'' He said, "About one.''
从200名减少到1名 好吧
I said, "From 200 to one? Okay.''
这绝对是个大灾难
That pretty well is a disaster.
我心想：
I thought, you know,
要么就找来几百个临时演员 要么就别找
either you have hundreds of extras or none.
不要随便找几个凑数
Rather than anything in between.
实际上我们一个都没找 让整个故事变得完全不同
The fact that we had none really set us up for a whole different kind of date
感觉非常冷清
of isolation,
我们就像完全暴露在外
of feeling incredibly exposed.
仿佛回到了童年
And it's all so childlike.
整个游乐场都属于我们自己
You know, you've got this big playground to yourselves
周围十分安静
and they would be a little less inhibited
没有拥挤的人群
than if there had been hundreds of people around.
结果非常令人满意
So, it all turned out for the best.
你不溜冰吗？
ADRIAN: Aren't you skating?
不 我不太喜欢溜冰
Now, I have no great love for ice skates.
我心想：好吧 我就在后面跟着她
I thought, "Okay. Rather than me just clonking around there,
洛奇为了哄她开心 什么都愿意做
"Rocky will do anything to make her feel good.
但是如果在此过程当中 样子必须傻一点 那也没关系
"But if he has to look foolish in the process, that's okay.''
我心想：这样已经够傻的了
And I thought this was about as foolish as it gets.
一个男人在冰上慢跑
A man jogging on ice.
我从不抱怨 因为我还在打拳
I still fight. I do it like a hobby.
问题是我是左撇子
The trouble is I'm a southpaw.
- 什么是左撇子？   - 左撇子就是惯用左手
-What's a southpaw? -A southpaw means you're left-handed.
我喜欢这个长镜头
I like these long shots here.
我觉得让人感觉到这里很冷清 是非常重要的
I think it's important to just sense the isolation
在他们的世界里 一切都那么遥远
and how remote everything is in their world.
他们远离生活的喧嚣
How distanced they are from the good things in life.
我猜就是在费城
He was fighting in the... I think it was around Philadelphia.
他也是左撇子 他的手臂朝向新泽西州
His arm... He was left-handed. His arm was facing...
当然 我觉得这是好事 是生活当中的小插曲
Or should I say, not the good things in life but the interaction in life.
很多人的世界都是非常狭小的
They don't interact with a lot of people, their world is extremely small.
与世隔绝
Very insulated.
事情可能会有好的结果
Things probably worked out for the best, don't you think?
你从没机会就因为你是左撇子？
Never got a chance because you're left-handed, huh?
一点不错
That's absolutely true, you know?
小心
Watch out.
在这里洛奇接触了她 我在《洛奇·巴尔博》的剧本当中也写到了这样的场面
When Rocky touches her here, I actually write about it in the new Rocky Balboa.
虽然她的手受伤了 这是他第一次接触她
Even though he twisted his finger, it's the first time he's ever touched her.
30年后 他说：
And he says, 30 years later,
“当我的手抓住她的胳膊”
when my hand grabbed her arm,
“可以感觉到她在颤抖”
he could feel a buzz. Even through all that wool coat, he could feel it.
- 我让你看样东西   - 七分钟！
-It ain't your fault. Look. -MAN: Seven minutes!
我会留着所有比赛的照片
I originally done it... I carry pictures of all my fights.
最早是克兰肖那场比赛
I originally done it in the Baby Crenshaw fight.
他的体型跟飞机一样
Baby's about the size of an airplane. I broke both hands on his face.
我曾经遇到过一位对手
I came across an ex-fighter once in a bar
他拿出钱包 说里面有他老婆孩子的照片
and he pulled out his wallet and instead of having pictures of his kids and his wife
还有他被打败的照片
he had pictures of himself getting beaten up.
他打输比赛时的照片
And even though he lost those fights,
那是一张很棒的照片
he goes, "Those are nice pictures.''
我说 “伙计 我总有一天会用这样的照片”
I said, "Man, I'm definitely gonna use that somewhere, someday.''
10年后
And 10 years later,
我也用了那样的照片
I used it.
你知道我是如何开始拳击的？
You know how I got started in fighting?
现在他们俩都已经消除了紧张感
Now he's starting to loosen up. They're both starting to loosen up.
现在她开始感觉到自由 滑冰滑得更加自在了
Now she's starting to feel free. She's skating freer.
她开始向他敞开心怀
She's now starting to relate a little bit.
他说他父亲说他生来不够聪明 不如好好善用身体
Talking about, he says that his father thought he never had much brains
她说她恰恰相反
and she's saying just the opposite.
知道我的意思吗？
You know what I mean?
你笑什么？
Why you laughing?
我母亲说的正好相反
My mother, she said the opposite thing.
所以他们很登对 她有聪明的头脑 他有强健的体魄
So they're kind of made for each other. She has the brains, he has the brawn.
也许会擦出火花
And they both have the sensitivity.
你生来不够健壮 不如好好善用你的头脑
!!So you better develop your brain.!!
- 她这么说？   - 时间到
-Did she say that? -Yo, time!
我能问你个问题吗？
Can I ask you a question?
喊“时间到”的那个人是乔治·曼莫里
He's a nice guy. The man who was yelling "time'' was George Memmoli.
他是一位优秀的演员 他…
He was a really good actor who was...
别跌倒 别跌倒…
ROCKY: Don't fall!
他是个演技派
really well used in Mean Streets.
我对这个还很内行
I'm pretty good at this.
你喜欢我溜冰的样子？
You like the way I skate?
我上一场和史派德·里柯的比赛？
Last fight I had, I had with this guy named Spider Rico.
他重击我的脑袋 有没有看到这伤疤？
He busted my head up there. You see that scar?
我告诉你 拳赛很艰苦
Ill tell you, things get pretty rough in the ring.
我写剧本的时候并没有注意
I wasn't aware of it when I was writing this,
可当我真正表演的时候
or actually performing it,
觉得洛奇的话说个没完
but Rocky is non-stop chatter.
他自己没感觉到
He doesn't censor himself
但是他一直说个不停
and he just goes on and on and on.
我想这正是吸引她的地方
And I think that's what appeals to her
让她感觉没有压力
is that he takes the pressure off of her speaking.
这又是我哥哥
Here's my brother again.
黑暗中的无赖
The bum from the dark.
去找份工作 无赖
Get a job, you bum!
他很会说话：你内向 我笨
But he's... You know, he'll say, "You know you're shy, I'm stupid,
我们是很配的一对
"we make a couple of perfect coconuts.''
他很会自我解嘲 我觉得吸引她的…
It's very, very self-effacing. I think that sort of appeals to her,
就是他完全不会评头论足
that he's completely non-judgmental
他对自己的感觉非常诚实
and very, very honest about his feelings towards himself.
不会幻想自己是大人物 也不浮夸
He has no illusions about who he is, or where he is going, which is nowhere.
我不明白为何有人想当拳击手
I don't understand why anybody would wanna be a fighter.
你一定是个白痴 才会想当拳击手 明白我的意思吗？
You gotta be a moron to wanna be a fighter, you know what I mean?
这是一个使你最终 成为无赖的行业
It's a racket where you're almost guaranteed to end up a bum.
- 我不认为你是无赖   - 至少也是半个无赖
-I don't think you're a bum. -I'm at least half a bum.
不过我要告诉你
But Ill tell you something.
拳击最痛苦的是第二天早晨
Worst thing about fighting is the morning after.
洛奇一直在抽烟 我觉得这很重要
Rocky is smoking all the time, in this. I thought it was important
表现出他没有任何运动 或者健康意识
to show that he has no athletic or health sensibilities whatsoever.
他是个小混混 多过拳击手
He's more of a hood than he is a fighter.
他开始过上了无赖的生活 因为他的拳击生涯已经结束了
He's being pulled into street life because his boxing days are over.
所以他觉得自己是个无赖
So he has a real street sense about him.
如果你看到洛奇·巴尔博
I mean, if you looked at Rocky Balboa
从街头走来 我想不到世界上有任何一个人…
coming down the street, there's no one in the world that I would think of,
会像他一样
that I can think of, who would say, "Boy, there goes an Olympic athlete.''
因为你不会唱歌或跳舞
'Cause you can't sing and dance?
对 类似那样
Yeah, something like that.
要不要进来坐坐？
Hey, you wanna come inside?
这是我最喜欢的场面之一 我并不担心
This is one of my favorite scenes. I wasn't aware of it, again at the time,
他站在门口的样子 就好像一只野兽
but the way he's hanging, from the door like an animal,
想用这间房子 留住这个姑娘
he's just embracing this house, and there he is beckoning to this poor girl
让她进入…
to come into this
这种怪异 不祥的状况
strange, foreboding situation.
他们应该把这张脸印在邮票上
They ought to stick this face on a stamp.
他一直在诱惑她
He's just trying to charm her and...
来 进来吧
Come on in.
这…我不知道
There's a... I don't know.
我想这是…
There's I guess a...
来吧
Yo, come on.
他这时候有点像孩子一样顽皮
? a real childlike quality about the kid.
我们看到他伸出一只黑色的手
That's my black hand coming out the..
好吧 她再一次陷入了犹豫
Again, she's at the crossroads.
任何一个女人跟那样的男人在那个时候走进那间房子
Any woman to walk into that place with that guy, at that time,
肯定都会印象深刻
has to be pretty much enamored with him.
开灯
Click.
艾德丽安 你饿吗？
Yo, Adrian, you hungry?
不
No.
我有些吃的
I got some things in there.
塔莉娅在这一幕当中的表现也很出色
Talia was great in this scene, too.
你可以看出她不想多走近一步
You can see that she doesn't want to go an inch more than she has to.
她走进这个房间之后 在外面感觉到的吸引力顿时消失了
She walked in there and, boy, the charm from outside just disappears.
她现在就好像在地狱 洛奇把帽子挂在墙上
She's in a hell hole. Rocky's putting his hat on a bayonet.
外套挂在架子上
His jacket on a machete.
2秒钟后 他把毛衣也脱了下来
And in two seconds, he's down to his tank top.
我想放些音乐
I could go for some music.
他装上唱片
Flips on the records.
浪漫的音乐 她站在那里12秒没有动
Roman tic music and they're not there for 12 seconds.
它们是我养的特别动物
These are the exotic animals I was telling you about.
但是他天真的举动再一次打动了她
But his childlike side kicks in with.
他说的第一件事 不是让她喝点什么
First thing he talks about are not a drink or anything,
“瞧瞧我的乌龟”
"Look at my turtles.''
还记得你在宠物店上班
...pet shop?
你第一天去上班我就买了
First day you was there, and I came in...
她的肢体语言 站在那里 一动不动
Well, her body language, the way she's just standing there, immobile.
买了这个鱼缸还有动物 饲料…
I bought this bowl and the animals themselves.
就像一个老妇人
Like a little old woman.
…底下的石子
.go on the bottom there.
记得那个假山吗？
Remember that mountain?
她有点不知所措
She's just paralyzed.
我把它丢了 它们一直会翻过来
...mountain. They kept falling over and flipping.
这张沙发…
The couch is something that...
你为何不过来坐？
Why don't you come over here and sit down?
我觉得需要一个特写镜头
.1 think you would need a polio shot.
这张沙发…上面都是啤酒瓶 乱七八糟的
The couch is diseased. Beer bottles stuck in it and whatever.
他说 “过来吧 这沙发很舒服”
And he goes, "Come on over, it's a nice couch.''
这里安全些
It's safer over here.
连她也笑了
Even she has to almost laugh at this.
I乙想：我得离开这儿
It's like, "Come on, I really got to get out of here.''
他们是你父母吗？
These your parents?
是 是他们两位
Yeah, that's both of them there.
这是你吗？
-Is this you? -Yeah. I was...
但是她慢慢的被吸引住了
But slowly she's being somewhat lured into...
因为她喜欢这个男人
'Cause she loves the guy.
你何不过来放轻松一点
Make yourself comfortable. Relax.
这是唯一一个注意到她的男人
He's the only man who's ever given her any attention, so...
但她还需要一点…
But she needs one more...
你有电话吗？
Do you have a phone?
再有一个…
Just one more...
我拆掉了 因为太多人打电话来
'Cause people calling all the time...
时刻 另一个诱因将她拉进去
? moment. Another hook to pull her in.
因为这时候她很矛盾   一边是她的传统观念
She's being torn in two directions. And this is her old sensibilities,
是她的负罪感 她作为基督徒的信念
this is her guilt, this is her Catholic upbringing saying,
告诉她：“我要离开这儿 因为这不符合”
"I got to get out of here, 'cause this goes against everything
“我的传统观念”
"that I've been brain washed into believing.''
保利 你妹妹在我家
Paulie! Your sister's with me!
我待会儿再打给你 回头见！
Ill call you back later! See you!
而洛奇却完全没有这种感觉 他知道如果她走了
And Rocky's just having none of it. He doesn't... He knows if she leaves,
对他来说一切都结束了
for him, it's like it's over.
他们不会再有机会相爱
It's a crushing defeat for any chance of them falling in love.
他也许永远不会找到一个合适的姑娘
He probably hasn't had a girl up there, maybe ever.
你不喜欢我？
You don't like me?
你不喜欢乌龟？还是其他的？
You don't like the turtles? What's the problem?
- 我觉得我不属于这里   - 没关系
-l don't think I belong here. -It's okay.
我不属于这里
I don't belong here.
没关系 因为你是我的客人
Well, you know, it's okay, 'cause you're my guest.
我说：“所有男人的房间都是一样的”
He's like, "All men's apartments are the same,''
“你不会觉得有什么区别”
and it's like, "I've never been in a man's apartment before.''
他做的一切 说的一切 都是为了把她留下
He's saying anything that... Just doesn't want to be abandoned.
男人都一样
They're all the same, you know?
我觉得还不够了解你
I'm not sure I know you well enough.
我浑身不自在
I don't feel comfortable.
我觉得他们非常诚实
See this is... This, I think, is really great, very honest.
她不自在 他也不自在
He's not comfortable either. She's not comfortable.
不过希望我们能创造出最棒的尴尬气氛
But let's make the best of an uncomfortable situation.
别走 拜托
Don't go, please. Don't go.
这也许是影片当中最出色的一段表演
This is maybe the best acting in the movie.
塔莉娅·夏尔表现了…
Talia Shire just goes through
50种情感 而且非常自然
fifty emotions without leaving that spot.
你知道你的眼睛很美吗？
You have nice eyes, you know?
再帮我一个忙
Do me another favor?
可以脱帽子吗？
Why don't you take off that hat?
任何想开始学习表演的人
If anybody ever wants to really study acting,
看看她在这一幕当中的表演
just check her out in this scene.
我一直知道你很漂亮
I always knew you was pretty.
- 别嘲笑我   - 我不是嘲笑你
-Don't tease me. -I'm not teasing you.
我没有嘲笑你
I ain't teasing you.
那种渴望 那种恐惧 那种期待的感觉
The longing, the desire, the fear, the anticipation.
她从来没接过吻
She's never been kissed.
如果不想 你可以不用吻我
You don't have to kiss me back if you don't wanna,
可是我想吻你
but I wanna kiss you.
感觉很微妙
Great. Just a nuance.
表演得很自然
Almost, she's still afraid to do it.
真的很棒
Brilliant stuff Great stuff
我知道这时候 她感觉并不好
It's also worth noting that at this time, she was not feeling well at all
但她很努力表演好这一幕
and she really dug down, and pulled that out
很棒的身体接触场面
under great physical duress.
我听说你有一场比赛
(GASPING)
对 我下个月有场拳赛
-MAN 1: Heard you had a fight coming up. -MAN 2: Next month.
1月 27 日
January 27, right?
来健身房 我们帮你锻炼
That's good. Come down to the gym.
这些都是真正的拳击手
These are all real fighters, Hurricane, Hart,
想争夺我的位置
Willy "The Worm'' Monroe.
迈克在找你
Mick was looking for you up there, man.
- 找我？你确定？   - 是的
-For me? You're sure? -Yeah, yeah.
他在找你 上去见他
He's looking for you. Get up there and see him.
- 他找我？   - 是的
-He wanted me? -Yeah. Your name's Rock, right?
是的 快去吧
-Yeah. -All right. Go on, babe.
讽刺的是当洛奇找到生活的意义时
The irony is that once Rocky seems to have found some kind of point to his life
至少他追到了艾德丽安
or at least an object of desire like Adrian,
事情就开始发生了变化   一切好像突然变得井然有序
things start to turn around. It begins to all of a sudden fall into place
艾德丽安给他带来了好运
like an avalanche of good luck.
他们要找人与阿波罗练拳
.sparring partners for Apollo Creed. There's the card.
- 他们何时来的？   - 约一小时前
-When was he here? -About an hour ago.
布吉斯…
And Burgess...
他们大概要找人与阿波罗练拳
Looking for sparring partners for Creed.
他的嫉妒心开始爆发
The jealousy here just has to erupt.
我说过了 你这个笨蛋！
...you dumb Dago!
从布吉斯的语气可以看出他很愤怒
Burgess actually came up with this idea of exploding here.
紧张的气氛从这里开始
Then we just built on it from here.
“你真的想知道？" “我要知道”
"You wanna know?'' "Yeah, I wanna know.''
- 你真的想知道？   - 我要知道！
-You wanna know? -I wanna know now!
好吧 我就告诉你
Okay, I'm gonna tell you!
你有成为拳击高手的天分
You had the talent to become a good fighter, and instead of that,
可是你却甘愿当狗腿子
you became a leg breaker for some...
他提到了他的才华 提到了他的能力
About lost potential, about abilities, that Rocky has...
你是在浪费生命
It's a waste of life!
洛奇根本不屑一顾 他并不像他说的那样
? ?taken the easy way, which he really hasn't,
但在布吉斯眼中 应该说是米奇的眼中 他就是个小混混
but in Burgess's eyes, or Mickey's eyes, he has.
可实际上米奇从来没有重视过他
But the truth is, Mickey really never gave him any attention
所以洛奇根本没有努力过
so Rocky never even tried. He was happy just...
他并不开心 但他很满足
Not happy but he was content.
过着小混混的生活 甘当一名失败的拳手
Just living his life as a street guy and a failed fighter,
做其他拳手的沙袋
basically a punching bag for other fighters.
你一定是洛奇·巴尔博先生
Oh, you must be Mr. Rocky Balboa.
杰更斯先生在等你 请等一下
Mr. Jergens's expecting you. Just a moment.
洛奇完全不是他的对手
So, Rocky's completely out of his league here.
这里也是制片人的办公室
This is also the producer's office.
洛奇又开始挥拳了
Rocky's still doing his twitching with his boxing.
他感到很不自在
Became like a tic after a while.
他要了一张卡片
I like when he asked for the card back.
他知道自己可能得不到这份工作 不过至少留作纪念也好
He knows he's probably not gonna get the job, but at least he has a souvenir.
巴尔博先生
Mr. Balboa.
你好吗？我是乔治·杰更斯
How are you? George Jergens.
请坐
Take a chair, please.
谢谢
Thanks.
在原来的剧本当中
The way this scene was written,
这一幕表现得很直白
it was pretty straightforward, the way it is now,
当主办人问他
except Rocky says
是否愿意跟阿波罗·克里德比赛的时候
to the promoter, when asked, "Would you like to fight Apollo Creed?''
他回答说：“愿意”
In the original screenplay he goes, "Yeah.''
可是经过我考虑之后
And I thought about it.
这个角色开始思考
As the character began to sink in and as I was playing it longer
至少我觉得… 我对这个角色更加了解
you start to... At least, I felt had a bit more of an understanding about the character.
我相信他没有足够的自信
And I believe that he didn't think enough about himself,
作为一名拳击手 他并没有什么技巧
you know, himself worthy, his skills, as a fighter, as a man,
根本不配跟阿波罗·克里德比赛
to even be in the same hemisphere as Apollo Creed.
所以他说 “不 我不想跟他比赛 我没资格 我只是个平庸的人”
So he goes, "No, I really don't wanna fight him. I'm not worthy, I'm a bum,
“我是个左撇子 但是我很感激你给我的机会”
"I'm a ham-and-egger, but I appreciate the opportunity.''
就像一个彩票中奖的人
Here's a man who's just won the lottery,
说他不该得到奖金
saying, "You know I really don't deserve it.
你可以把钱收回 送给其他人
"You can have it back. Give it to someone else.''
然而主办人必须说服他 否则他会被炒鱿鱼
And it takes the promoter, who has to get him or he will be fired.
他现在用“美国遍地都是机会”
Now he's got to con him in this about America being the land of opportunity,
等一切办法来诱惑他
and all this flag-waving to seduce him.
阿波罗就相信
Apollo Creed does...
然而洛奇觉得
Whereas Rocky would have just been happy to take the meeting
只要能当他的训练伙伴就很满足了
and be used as a sparring partner and that's it.
他没有想过要跟他比赛
He had no intentions.
这也许是他的噩梦成真了
As a matter of fact, this may be a nightmare come true,
因为他觉得自己根本没资格 跟这个人共处一室
'cause he doesn't have what it takes to even be in a room with this man.
所以他很害怕
So he's scared.
非常害怕
Very scared.
各位 照片拍够了
All right, fellas. That's enough pictures.
我们要问阿波罗几个问题
We wanna ask Apollo a few questions.
你对这座兄弟之爱的城市有何感想？
Apollo, how do you like the City of Brotherly Love?
到了费城令我充满爱国心
APOLLO: Well, just being in Philadelphia makes me feel patriotic.
街上友善的人都祝福我
Beautiful people in a...
当你的命运改变时 周围的人对你的态度也会随之改变
Now, as fortunes change, so do the attitudes of people around you,
尤其是保利
and especially now Paulle.
他的嫉妒心已经不再掩藏
His jealousy begins to no longer stay well-hidden.
慢慢浮现出来
It's simmering to the top.
并且逐渐泛滥
And just overflowing.
你们没听说过 福治河谷或邦克山战役吗？
Didn't you guys ever hear of Valley Forge or Bunker Hill?
阿波罗 阿波罗
Apollo?
你在二百周年纪念国庆日
It is a coincidence that you're fighting a white man
出战白人是巧合吗？
on the most celebrated day in the country's history?
我不知道 那他在建国二百周年纪念日
I don't know. Is it a coincidence that he's fighting a black man
出战黑人也是巧合吗？
on the most celebrated day in the country's history?
- 正是   - 说的好 兄弟
-Right on, Apollo! -Tell the truth, brother!
你对挑战者有何感觉？
Listen, Apollo. How do you feel about...
当他在电视里看到这个节目
Rocky's definitely watching this on TV, it's like,
从电视里看到自己 感觉非常离奇
to see himself on television there, it's just surreal.
如果你仔细看的话 会发现
He can't even take it seriously.
天啊 他那么单纯
It's like, "My God!'' He's so unsophisticated, and he's just...
不怕被人嘲笑 他觉得没有关系
It's okay to be mocked. It doesn't bother him. It's all right.
“别太在意了 保利”
Don't take it so seriously, Paulle.
你准备如何迎战阿波罗·克里德？
Rocky, how do you expect to fight Apollo Creed?
可是保利露出了本性
Oh, jeez, you know...
一再出言讥讽
But Paulie, being who he is, just trying to antagonize and antagonize.
洛奇 悄悄告诉我
Rocky, just between us,
意大利种马的绰号哪里来的？
where did you get the name !!Italian Stallion!!?
我在八年前吃晚餐时想到的
Oh, I invented that about eight years ago when I was eating dinner.
洛奇 现在你的酬劳高达十五万美元
Rocky, now your payday will be$150,000.
有没有任何想法
Any comment?
- 我…没有   - 你没有意见 对吧 洛奇？
-You got no comment, Rocky, right? -No.
- 谢谢 洛奇…   - 等一下
-Thank you, Rocky. -Wait a minute.
我想跟我女朋友打个招呼 好吗？
I just wanna say hi to my girlfriend, okay?
艾德丽安 是我 洛奇！
Yo, Adrian, it's me, Rocky.
在这里他引起了一场骚动
This is, to him, worth the whole odyssey here.
他觉得能够从电视上
Being able to say to Adrian,
跟艾德丽安打招呼
to call her out and say hello from television,
是一件很神奇的事 当然保利一直在出言刺激他
is like amazing, so of course Paulie again is antagonizing
然而博学多才的艾德丽安 为他解了围
and Adrian, who is well-read, comes to the rescue
她提到了一些残障人士
and brings up facts about other people being somewhat impaired
最后获得成功的例子 比如海伦·凯勒和贝多芬
and rising to the surface. There's Helen Keller and Beethoven.
把洛奇比喻成他们 我觉得很好笑
And putting Rocky in that league, I thought was funny.
…替你递毛巾 或是打点杂务知道吗？
? .and someone standing by with a towel or running errands?
保利 从前有谁关心过我？没有
Hey, yo, Paulie, who cared about me yesterday? Nobody.
所以我打算自我训练
So I just think I'm gonna train myself, you know?
没有好人帮你的话
Without such good people around to help you,
你根本没机会
you don't have such a good chance.
爱因斯坦被退学两次
Einstein flunked out of school twice.
是吗？
That so?
没错 贝多芬是聋子 海伦·凯勒是瞎子
Yeah. Beethoven was deaf. Helen Keller...
我已经从塔莉娅·夏尔的角色中看出 她已经开始有主见
I can already see in Talia Shire's character, she's starting to grow roots.
变得越来越强势
She's becoming stronger, and it's aggravating the hell
开始敢于顶撞哥哥
out of her brother now.
波特的表演很出色
And Burt plays this great.
别干涉我的生活！
Keep out of my freaking life!
- 我做了什么？   - 没有
-What'd I do? -Nothing.
我说错话了吗？
Did I say something wrong?
你什么都没说
You didn't say nothing. It's all right.
没错 你什么都不帮我说！
That's right! You didn't say nothing!
一句都没有！
Nothing at all!
波特·杨的手势很独特
Burt Young's hand gestures are unique on the planet.
没有一个人能模仿他的手势
No one can move his hands the way Burt Young can move his hands.
很能表现出个性
Just very expressive, very expressive.
没啤酒了吗？
We ain't got any beer?
你应该买些啤酒的
I thought you were supposed to pick up some beer!
我觉得这一幕同样也 很能表现出人物个性
I think this scene also says a lot about the character.
他说 “这种事情没什么大不了”
"This stuff don't bother me. Doesn't bother me.''
但他只对她承认…
But he will admit to her, and to no one else that...
你为何那么做？
Why'd you do that?
你在骗我对吗？
You're putting me on, right?
事情的确有了转机
Things do eat at him.
他一生都在被当作笑柄
He's been a joke his whole life,
也许这一次他能有所作为 他不确定结果如何
and maybe this time he can do something, he's not sure what yet,
但是他要得到一些自尊
to gather some self-respect, that's all.
就是为了这个目的
Just some self-respect.
我说过电视上那段话没什么大不了的
You know how I said that stuff on TV didn't bother me?
是吗？
Yeah.
其实不然
It did.
这里是费城的一个…
Very famous locale in Philadelphia called Pat's Steak House.
著名的训练基地
And it's like...
我还有些钱
I got a few dollars.
他在这里仍然叼着烟
? where he would naturally hang out. Here he is, still smoking,
在他面临人生最重要的一场比赛 参加训练之前
on the eve of beginning to train for the biggest moment of his life,
旧习惯 原来的小混混作风
the old habits, the old street, the call of the wild here,
他仍然改不掉
is still strong with him.
即使连放高利贷的人 都希望他能好好表现
And even the loan shark wants him to better himself.
- 等一下   - 什么事？
-GAZZO: Wait a minute. -What?
好好训练
You're in training. Come on.
好像洛奇表现好了 就等于他们都表现好了
It's like if Rocky performs, they all perform.
洛奇·巴尔博唯一的朋友
That's the only friend Rocky Balboa has,
无论你是否相信 就是他的债主
believe it or not, is his employer.
除了保利 就是这个放高利贷的
There's Paulie, his loan shark employer.
他没有什么朋友
He doesn't have any relationships.
所以连他的债主都成了他的朋友
So it means a lot that even the loan shark would show up.
布吉斯·梅迪斯出现在这一幕当中
This is the brilliant Burgess Meredith coming up to do a scene
他表演得非常出色
that really grew during the performance.
跟剧本中描述的一样
On the page, it was pretty much there.
我稍后再解释发生了什么事
I'll explain later on what did happen,
可我觉得这是…
but this is, I think, pretty.
哪位？
ROCKY: Yeah.
我觉得这是很多人在生活当中 都会遇到的难题
I think this is a dilemma that a lot of people have in their lives,
几乎每个人都会有
that probably almost everyone has,
这是一个错失的机会 他们从来没有机会
that it was a missed opportunity,
展现他们的才能
that they never got the chance to show what they had.
所以如果他们不能当千里马
So, if they can't do it,
至少能够当伯乐 找到一匹千里马
at least they can be involved with someone else who can do it.
但是如果他恰恰是你一直毗之以鼻的人 那又该如何启齿？
And how do you do that after you've belittled someone their entire life?
就像米奇一直看不起洛奇
Like Rocky had been belittled by Mickey.
这又是一个父与子之间的关系
So this again, this is the father-son situation where the father
父亲一直觉得儿子没有能耐
who had taken his son for granted, had been belittling him his whole career,
从来都看不起他 就像很多父亲都 会说 “你看看人家…”
saying, like a lot of fathers say, "Why can't you be like that kid next door?
“你为什么就不能像别人那么聪明？"
"Why can't you be as smart as that fellow down the street?''
可后来当他发现
Then the time comes, you find out, "Well, you know what?
他的儿子很有本事 出乎他的意料
"Your son has a lot going on here, a lot more than you thought.''
现在你只能放下架子
And now you have to eat crow
回来哄他
and come back and try to trick him,
或者动之以情
or pull on his heartstrings.
你不该得到第二次机会
When you really don't deserve a second shot...
你不会有第二次机会
You ain't gonna get a second chance.
因为你以前那样对待他
after the way you've treated him.
对 没错
All right.
你想过了吗？
You thought of that, huh?
你现在需要的是一个经纪人
Well, what you need is a manager.
经纪人 听我的准没错
A manager. Listen to me.
我知道 因为我在这行待了五十年
I know, because I been in this racket for 50 years.
- 五十年？   - 五十年 天啊 我全见过了
-50 years, huh? -50 years. I've seen it all.
全部 你知道我做了什么？
-All of it. You know what I done? -What?
这时候洛奇明白到来者不善 他可不吃这一套
At this point Rocky knows what's coming and there's no way he's buying into this.
尤其是对于这个
Especially from this man
他非常不喜欢的人
who he pretty much dislikes.
同一天晚上 傅波击败了丹西
...the same night that Firpo knocks Dempsey out of the ring.
结果谁名声大噪？你猜猜
So who gets the publicity? Figure that out.
- 丹西   - 没错 可为什么？
-Dempsey. -That's right. But why?
- 因为他曾是冠军   - 错 因为他有经纪人
-'Cause he was champ. -No! Because he had a manager.
而我却没有
I had nothing.
我给你看样东西 你看我的脸
I wanna show you something. I want you to look at my face.
我左眼缝了21针
Look at this. I got 21 stitches over this left eye.
右眼缝了34针
I got 34 stitches over this eye.
鼻子被打断17次
You know I had my nose busted 17 times.
可以洛奇的性格
Rocky, by virtue of his character,
他没有胆量说“滚蛋”
just doesn't have the stomach to say, "Get out.''
只能让这个老头子喋喋不休
And he's allowing this old man to ramble on
用尽一切方法哄他
and use every trick in the book
奉承他 拍他马屁
to cajole him and flatter him into hiring him
希望他能请他当经纪人
as a trainer, as a manager.
- 你真的那么想   - 没错
-You really think so? -That's right.
你的动作很像他 你有他那样的决心
You move like him, and you got heart like he did.
对 我有决心…
Yeah, I got heart, but I ain't got...
我想在一个人的一生当中
It gets right down to little things in one's life.
雪中送炭总是胜于锦上添花
A little kindness at the right time would have been appreciated.
对他来说更是如此
There's a lesson in there.
当我踏入这一行时…
You know, when I begun in this business, kid...
听着 我有个建议 赛前千万别喝那种东西
I wanna make a suggestion. Don't drink that piss before a fight.
对你有害无益
It's no good for you.
你不介意我这么说吧？
If you don't mind my saying.
当我踏进这一行
Anyway, you know, when I started in this racket,
我们这种三流的拳手
pugs like us, we was treated like dogs.
洛奇并没有飞镖盘 他只是将飞镖射到门上
Now, Rocky doesn't have a dartboard. He just throws his darts into a door.
我觉得这是他的方式…
And I thought this is his way of, kind of like...
有一次一个混蛋和我比赛
.this son of a bitch that I fought,
用将飞镖射到门上来发泄他的怨气
? countering everything Burgess is saying by throwing these missiles into a wall.
鲜血从我脸颊喷出来
I had spit shooting out of my cheeks.
你能想像吗？
Can you imagine that?
他根本没有在意
Not paying attention at all.
他用尽一切办法使自己分心
Anything to distract himself from having to stay in one spot and listen.
不听他说的话 觉得他很可怜
It's getting to him. It's getting pathetic, sad,
这个家伙想方设法诱惑他
to see this man pull out every trick in the book.
甚至还拿出了照片
He didn't take care of the picture.
洛奇很单纯 他不是米奇的对手
There is a naivety about Rocky, that he just is no match for Mickey.
我要把它传给你
I wanna give it to you.
他是只老狐狸
His intensity. There's no match.
我要照顾你
I wanna take care of you.
确定发生在我身上的不幸 不会发生在你身上
I wanna make sure that what happened to me doesn't happen to you.
明白我的意思吗
You know what I mean?
比赛已经确定了
Mick, the fight's set.
听我说 我要当你的经纪人
Listen to me. I wanna be your manager.
你同意吗？
You follow that?
比赛已经确定了 我不需要
Fight's set. I don't need no manager.
我要给你的东西是买不到的
But you can't buy what I'm gonna give you.
我有过痛苦及经验
I got pain and I got experience.
我也有过痛苦及经验
I got pain and I got experience too.
听着 孩子
Listen, kid.
你给我听好
Hey, Mick.
我十年前需要你的帮助
I needed your help about 10 years ago, right?
这是真的 “我很久以前需要你的帮助”
This is so true. He needed your help a long time ago
“可你从来不屑一顾 而现在我有了…”
and you were never there and now, I've got a little something...
“展露锋芒的好机会 你就想来分一杯羹”
Someone's tossed me a few crumbs and you want that.
“我宁愿自己一个人参赛 也不需要一个伪君子的帮忙”
I'd rather go in there alone, than with someone who really doesn't care
“你只不过想再来占我便宜”
and they're just here to take advantage of me again.
到了这一刻 这一幕已经结束了
Now, the scene was over at this point.
他走了出去 洛奇以为他离开了
And he comes out, Rocky thinks he's left,
他打开门再次见到他 无法面对他
comes out, sees him again, he can't face him.
因为他知道再这样下去 他会接受他的请求
Just 'cause he knows if he does he'll accept it.
他不忍心拒绝这个老头子
He doesn't have the heart to turn the old man down.
所以我觉得洛奇应该说点什么
So, I thought, Rocky's got to say something.
他应该报复 电影当中应该有一刻…
He's got to vent, there's got to be a moment in this film
让他把心里话都说出来
where he just lets it all out.
但是他没有胆量在别人面前说
But he doesn't have the guts to do it in front of somebody.
他不是那种人
He's not that kind of guy.
所以他只对着空屋抱怨
So, he'll just talk to an empty room.
其实是在自言自语 说出他内心的独白
He'll vent to himself basically. His inner monologue.
这是他内心多年以来的感受
This is what he's really been carrying around inside for years
根本没有人知道
that no one knows about.
所有人都觉得他是个开心的幸运小子
Everyone thinks, "He's sort of a happy-go-lucky dumbbell.''
但是他满肚子怒气
But he has a lot of rage in there.
内心很受伤 很愤怒
A lot of hurt. A lot of angst.
至少你还有过全盛期 我什么都没有
I ain't had no prime. I ain't had nothing.
日复一日 我什么都不是
Legs are going, everything is going. Nobody's giving me nothing.
有人提议我出赛 没什么了不起
Guy comes up, offers me a fight. Big deal.
想比赛吗？好 我就打一场
Wanna fight the fight? Yeah, I'll fight the big fight.
如果我不打 下场又是如何？
I'm gonna go fight that big fight and I'm gonna get that!
我一定要打
I'm gonna get that!
你想来看我比赛？
And you wanna be ringside and see?
是不是？你想帮助我？
Do you? You wanna help me out?
你想看我被狠狠修理一顿？
Do you wanna see me get my face kicked in?
如果你几年前教我该怎么打拳 我也许会有机会
If you'd just shown me how to fight years earlier, I might've had a chance.
但是我只有挨打的份
But I'm gonna get slaughtered.
对 我会跟他打
Yeah, Ill fight him.
如果你以前注意到我的话
If you'd just given me a little bit of attention.
狠狠被他修理一顿
Get my face kicked in.
你来找我 想搬来一起住吗？
And you come around here. You wanna move in with me?
来啊 我的房子很棒！
Come on in. It's a nice house!
真的很棒 赶快搬进来 它很臭
Real nice! Come on in! It stinks!
他的一生都很糟糕
His whole life stinks.
你想帮助我？
You wanna help me out?
但是
Well, help me out!
最后
But in the end...
我就站在这里
I'm standing here!
他知道自己一个人做不到
...he knows he can't do it alone.
他可以明白
And he kind of understands
老头子的意图
the old man's plight, too.
这个角色富有同情心
There's a compassion about the character,
洛奇的世界里 所有人都很矛盾
that everyone in Rocky's world is conflicted.
如果有时候你能接受
And if you just accept it sometimes,
只要这个人心地并不坏
as long as the guys aren't blatantly cruel, they're conflicted.
他很气愤 因为他总是一事无成 我是说米奇
He's an angry man who never made it. I'm talking about Mickey.
洛奇能够理解 因为他也正在走米奇的老路
Rocky can identify with that because he was on his way to becoming like Mickey.
也感到很痛苦
Embittered, too.
所以在这一刻 他可以给这人带来一个新希望
So here, they have a moment perhaps. He can give this man a new lease on life
而老头子也许能帮助他
and the old man can actually, perhaps, help him survive a bit longer
在没有别人的帮助下 支撑得更久些
than he normally would have survived without anyone's help.
诺曼斯岛
No man's an island.
(RINGING)
以前在纽约 六七十年代的时候 我根本没什么钱
Early on in New York, in 1969, 1970, I didn't have much money at all
有一间小房子
and I had this little room.
天啊 每个月大约70美元
Oh, my God, it was about$70 a month, very small room,
没有冰箱 所以我会到外面
and it didn't have a refrigerator, so I would go out
杂货店去买一些鸡蛋和酸奶之类的
to the local delicatessen, wherever, and buy a dozen eggs and some yoghurt
放在窗外
or something like that, and keep it on the windowsill.
通常酸奶会被鸟吃光
And quite often the birds would eat most of the yoghurt or whatever,
不过它们把蛋留下来
but the eggs, they'd leave alone.
所以每天早晨我伸手去拿那些蛋 都已经冻成冰了
And every morning, I would reach out, when they weren't frozen,
我会把半打鸡蛋打到一个杯子里
and take about a half dozen eggs in a glass,
因为我没有炉子 所以就直接生喝下去
and since I didn't have a stove, drink it raw.
我不知道这样好不好
And I thought, "God, I don't know if this is good,
但似乎很有营养
"but it seems like it would be healthy.''
几年之后 五年之后在我拍《洛奇》的时候
Here I am, years later, five years later, doing Rocky.
重演了一回我以前连续好几年 每天早上做的事
I said, "I might as well re-enact what I did every morning for years.''
后来我发现这很不健康
Then I found out it's really unhealthy to do this.
但我已经练习过无数次了
But I'd had a lot of practice doing it.
现在只有28华氏度 冷死人了
It's 28. It's awfully chilly.
出门前记得多穿几件衣物
Make sure you have it bundled up before you bring it out.
也许洛奇是唯一一个把毛衣 手L在裤子里的人
Rocky is probably the only man who also ever tucked his sweatshirt into his pants.
而这条运动裤看上去像是 他14岁时穿的
And his sweatpants looked like they fit him maybe when he was 14.
他从来没买过新的
Never bothered to buy new ones.
这可以表现出他的无私
Just something about him that's completely selfless, so you couldn't...
他在背后画上了“意大利种马”的标志
A little Magic Marker on the back with "Italian Stallion.''
再一次展现出他的命运
Again that predisposition thing that's...
这是唯一可以突出他的特色的方式
That's his only way to differentiate himself,
这个绰号
was his little name.
不过我很喜欢这个镜头 从这个角度看着他跑出去
I love this shot though. It's like this old, rusty engine trying to start its way up.
感觉他好像完全与世隔绝
The entire town asleep, but him. Completely isolated.
大部分的镜头都是我们偷拍的
When we were taking most of these shots, we were just stealing them.
没有任何准备 我们没有任何设备
Literally jump out of a van. There was no motor home to speak of.
我可以告诉你
There was nothing.
所有人都是在旅行车后面换衣服
Everyone changed in the back of a station wagon.
我们顺道拍了这些画面
So, we'd grab these shots.
我记得当我住在费城的时候
I remember when I lived in Philadelphia,
会去这个博物馆 偶尔去看一下
I would go to this museum, just look at it once in a while,
利用那里的楼梯 是个很棒的主意
and this idea of using it, the steps, this incredible
这座博物馆是个壮观的建筑
place of higher learning, this museum's extraordinary structure,
蓝色的街道和这些阶梯
and this blue-collar street pug running up these steps,
构成的背景 我觉得很有意思
set against that background, I thought was really kind of interesting,
这座建筑很美
and it was such a beautiful structure.
洛奇穿着旧运动服 几乎爬不上这些楼梯
Here's Rocky in an old tattered sweatshirt, barely able to get up these steps.
这里看起来像是古希腊的神殿
It almost looked like some Greek pantheon.
当时 我们并没有想到这会变成
At the time, we had no idea that this would become one of the more,
《洛奇》当中最有代表性的场景之一
I guess you'd call it, iconic shots in Rocky.
这只是我们随意拍的
It was just something that we grabbed while we could.
结果却令人感到惊喜
Funny how things work out.
别这样
Come on.
这里很臭 你知道吗？
It stinks in here, you know?
我知道
Yeah. I know.
保利在他的世界里
Now, Paulie is in his world.
非常自在 虽然他不喜欢自己的工作
Where he's very comfortable, even though he doesn't like his job.
但是你可以看到他在这里 可以愚弄洛奇
But you can see, now he can mess with Rocky here.
他在这些肉块当中十分快活
He's very comfortable among all these slabs of meat,
而洛奇却不知所措
and Rocky is very out of place.
他好像是第一次去那种地方
I was frightened the first time we'd ever been there.
不付钱给盖索的下场就是这样
If you don't pay Gazzo, you end up on a hook.
你也知道盖索是好人
Gazzo's a good man. You know that.
别紧张 我知道
Don't get excited. I know that.
所以我才要你帮我引见
That's why I wanted you to talk to him about me and the collecting job.
好让我离开这个臭气冲天的地方
And can get me out of this stinking freezer.
帮自己一个忙 你何不继续做 因为待遇较好
Why don't you do yourself a favor? Keep this job. You eat better.
现在他…
This is where he...
他又在刺激保利
Now he's pushed Paulie's button for the last time.
保利想让他给介绍份工作 又遭到了拒绝
He's asked him for a job, he's turned him down again.
这个地方死气沉沉的
And there's something about this place that is so dead,
非常残酷 非常阴冷 保利一直想…
so brutal, so cold, that Paulie has to live in,
走出这个困境
that speaks volumes for his dilemma,
他感到绝望
his sense of hopelessness.
我不知道 我想她能填补我的不足
I don't know. Fills gaps, I guess.
什么不足？
What's "gaps''?
我不知道 就是不足 她有不足 我也有不足 我们互补不足之处
I don't know. She's got gaps. I got gaps. Together we fill gaps.
现在他的嫉妒心又开始作崇了
Now the jealousy starts to surface itself
因为他没有想到自己的妹妹
because he didn't really think his sister and Rocky
竟然跟洛奇这么合得来
would ever hit it off like this.
他很怕家里只剩下他一人独守空房
Now he's afraid he's gonna be left with no one in the house,
失去了工作 妹妹也离开了
no job with Gazzo, no sister, nothing.
因为你是大嘴巴 话太多
Because you got a big mouth. You just talk too much.
- 这里面真冷 我要回家   - 这里冷
-It's cold in here. I'm going home. -Cold in here?
这里不只冷
It is cold in here!
还很臭 你也很臭
It stinks in here, and you stink!
对于那些没有试过 把猪肉当沙包的人来说 我不建议这么做
For those who've never punched a side of beef, I don't recommend it.
并没有看上去这么简单
It's not as easy as it looks.
真的有点疼
It definitely hurts a little bit.
你把肋条打断了
You're breaking the ribs.
我觉得这里用到了象征手法
But the symbolism here, I think, speaks volumes.
保利第一次发现 他未来的妹夫
Paulie realizes that, for the first time, that his future brother-in-law, here,
不仅仅是个街头小混混
is not just, you know, this goofy street guy,
如果他被逼急了 也会表现出可怕的一面
that he has a whole other dark side to him if you push him in that direction.
最后他们还是喜欢对方
In the end, they still like each other.
明早见好吗？
Ill see you tomorrow morning, okay?
无论如何 这两个人之间有一枚炸弹
Whatever problems they have, they just... There's a bond between these two.
他对他又爱又恨
It's a true love-hate...
- 我把暖气打开了   - 谢谢
-ADRIAN: I turned the heat up. -ROCKY: Thanks.
你哥哥是个好人 但太强势 你知道吗？
Your brother's a good man, but he's awful pushy, you know?
- 要我帮你按摩吗？   - 不 我只是酸痛
-You want me to rub you down? -No, I'm just sore, okay?
- 我坐一下就好   - 你确定？
-I'm gonna just sit here. -You sure?
嗯 我确定
Yeah, I'm sure.
这一幕很有意思
This is kind of an interesting scene because it's the first time
因为这是我们第一次看到 洛奇想要自己呆会儿
that we see Rocky just wanting to be left alone.
他很疼 而且…
He's hurting and he's getting, I think,
对将要面对的比赛感到十分紧张
anxious about what's coming up. But he's in way over his head,
他很疲倦
and he's exhausted.
即使是他的最爱 显然他最爱的是
Even the thing that he loves the most, the object he loves the most,
艾德丽安
Adrian, is...
在这个时刻他也想避开 这时他再次充满了内疚感
He just isn't in a position at this moment... Then again, the guilt sets in.
这是在他人生当中很少遇到的时刻
So, right at this point, it's the most confused time of his life.
但他知道…我总觉得拳击手的生命…
But he knows. I always thought that the fight is one hour out of his life.
她就是他的生命
She is his life.
- 我没关系   - 我很抱歉
-IVs okay. -I'm sorry.
很美好的一幕
Beautiful little scene.
显然洛奇的训练方式
A gain Rocky's workout outfit, compared to everyone else's,
非常与众不同
is quite distinct.
他只是一只野兽
He's just a different animal.
打得满身大汗 根本没有任何技巧
Old, sweaty, torn up grays, there's no sense of style or...
我的步伐一直不好
I never had good footwork.
先别管步伐 你根本不平衡
Never mind footwork. Now you're all balanced.
马西安诺也有同样问题
Marciano had the same problem
绳子解决了它
and this string cured it.
都是训练方法问题
It's all about the work.
重点是你移动及出拳时不扯断绳子
If you can move and hit without breaking the string, you got balance!
就有平衡感了 到时候你就是危险人物
You become a dangerous person.
洛奇 你看来不错
-You follow me? -Looking good, Rock.
- 谢谢   - 开始吧
-Thanks. -Let's go. That's it.
- 现在用力打   - 就是这样 注意底下
-Underneath it. -WOMAN: Hey, Rock.
训练也很重要
He's got discipline, too.
滚出去！
Get out of here!
这样很好 因为洛奇从来没有训练过
That is great, 'cause Rocky has no discipline.
他有职业道德
He has a work ethic, in a sense, if he gets going,
但从来没有人指导过他
but he's never had anyone really to lay it out to him,
重要的是
what it's all about.
如果你想成为一流的运动员
"You wanna be a first-class athlete,
就要放弃你最爱的东西
"you got to give up the things you love the most.''
比如 对他来说 是艾德丽安
Like, well, for him, Adrian.
好 不再乱来
Okay, no more fooling around.
很好 开始练拳
Okay. Now hit it.
女人会让你软脚？
Women weaken legs, huh?
喂 洛奇 洛奇
-GIRL 1: Yo, Rock. -GIRL 2: Yo, Rocky.
没有一个人像他那样
Imagine someone coming down the street like that, just punching away.
边跑边挥拳的
You'd throw a net over him.
你好漂亮
You look great.
- 真的？   - 当然
-Really? -Oh, yeah. Terrific.
这对他来说就像圣诞节
This is like a Christmas day for him.
艾德丽安打扮得很漂亮
Adrian has really come full circle. Or just about full circle.
我还有个惊喜给你
-I got another surprise for you. -What?
她正当青春貌美 找到了生活的意义
She has blossomed to the hilt. She has now got something to live for.
那只狗 实际上那是我的狗
And the dog, my God, this is actually my dog, so...
它可以陪你练跑步
To keep you company when you run.
所以他很听话
He was pretty well trained to do everything.
我们相处得很愉快
Very comfortable with one another.
进来见见我的家人 主人都不会回来领它？
Come in and meet the family. The owner never come back?
后来有一幕
There was a scene that followed this,
洛奇在那里看信
up there where Rocky starts reading some hate mail,
我想就是在这里结束的
and I thought we'd just end it right here.
另一幕是在这里
Or the editors thought that we should have ended it here.
(BARKING)
我想再一次提到保利
Once again, I just want to bring back Paulie,
他在这一段当中被遗忘了
who's been pretty much left out of this scenario.
他在想方设法参与其中
He's doing everything he can to get a piece of the action, just be part of it.
他知道他将失去自己的妹妹
He knows that he's losing his grip on his sister,
也许现在洛奇对他来说更加重要
and perhaps, Rocky. Rocky is now more important than he is.
看你训练
To watch you train.
所以他在出谋划策
So he's making like he's setting him up,
想让洛奇变得更出名 想让他家喻户晓
he's making Rocky more famous, he's going to make him a household name,
为他做广告
good advertising.
看见这只雪茄吗？ 把它插进自己耳朵
See this cigar? I'm gonna stick it in your ear.
把它插进自己耳朵 你应该先打电话或留言
Don't do these things to me. You should've called me.
别再这么做
Leave a message. Don't do that.
我妹妹真的喜欢你
My sister really likes you.
我发誓总有一天会杀了你
I'm gonna kill you one of these days!
来吧 来吧
Come on.
- 宝贝   - 宝贝
-Baby! -Baby.
他来了 未来的重量级拳王 洛奇·巴尔博！
Here he is, the next heavyweight champion of the world, Rocky Balboa!
洛奇·巴尔博
Hello there. Rocky Balboa.
我们想简短访问你 不会很久的
We wanna get a brief interview with you.
她是一位真正的记者
This is an actual reporter, Diana Lewis, from the area.
我觉得…
And I thought that...
我一直都相信 如果要找人 在电影当中饰演记者
I've always believed that when you're going to use a reporter in a film,
就找一名真正的记者 他们的态度 他们说话的模式 以及肢体语言
a news reporter, there's just an attitude, a speech pattern and body language
是演员很难模仿的
that is very hard for actors to duplicate.
我觉得很难演好这样的角色
I find that I've never been convinced by it ever, so...
不 我不会的
No, I won't do that.
我们要找一位真实的记者
We want the real deal here.
今天我们访问重量级拳王挑战者 洛奇·巴尔博
Today we're here with heavyweight challenger Rocky Balboa.
- 今天访问的目的…   - 那家伙跑到镜头里来了
The reason we're standing in this...
CAMERAMAN: The meat guy's sticking his face in.
我们再来一次 洛奇
Let's try it again, Rocky.
今天我们访问重量级拳王挑战者 洛奇·巴尔博
Today we're here with heavyweight challenger Rocky Balboa.
我们在冷冻库访问的原因
The reason we're standing in this refrigerated box
是因为他的训练方式与众不同
is that Mr. Balboa has an unusual method of training.
稍后他将为各位观众示范
In a moment, he'll demonstrate that for the viewing audience at home.
首先 你怎么想到在此训练？
But first, Rocky, how did you come to train in an icebox?
我们从镜头转到了现实当中
This is where reality is beginning to set in
来到了阿波罗·克里德的训练营 阿波罗希望…
on the Apollo Creed camp, and Apollo is so interested
能利用这一时刻来赚钱
in exploiting the moment, and making money out of this,
他根本不理会对手是谁 为了什么跟他比赛
he has lost sight of who he's fighting and what the man is fighting for.
我相信任何一个拳击手
And I believe that anyone who's willing to throw caution to the wind
参加比赛都会有自己的目的 而他是为了钱
and has something worth fighting for, and not just money,
他面对的是一个非常危险的对手
something that's much deeper, is a very, very dangerous opponent.
他的教练是由托尼·伯顿饰演的
And his trainer, played by Tony Burton, realized that,
他发现阿波罗对这场比赛 想法太天真了
and Apollo, of course, is naive to the fact.
中西部十五个电台呢？
in the Midwest?
你的钱还是用于 加拿大的公众上吧
You can spend your money better in Canadian publicity.
我在多伦多有朋友
By the way, Apollo, I've got friends in Toronto
可以帮你节税
who can get you a good tax break.
乔治 我喜欢你的朋友
George, I like your friends.
我觉得任何不注重细节的人
So, anyone who fails to pay attention to details,
尤其是在生死关头 注定会失败
especially when it's a life-and-death situation, is doomed to failure.
- 看来他是玩真的   一对 我也是真的赚大钱
-Looks like he means business. -APOLLO: Yeah, I mean business too.
还有咖啡吗？
Shirley, we got any more coffee out there?
当然有 我马上去拿
SHIRLEY: Certainly, Mr. Creed. I'll get you some right away.
比赛完我干脆退休选享乐好了
APOLLO: After the fight, I may retire and run for emperor.
他打得非常起劲
He does this very well, Tony Burton.
台词表现出他的内心世界 但是他的肢体语言表达得更多
His eyes say a lot. His body language says even more.
我是黛安娜·路易斯 在冷冻库…
Diana Lewis in the meat house...
这个画面很有意思
What an image.
与左撇子洛奇·巴尔博
.with southpaw Rocky Balboa.
再一次回到了费什镇
Once again, back in Fishtown,
波特·杨饰演的保利
Burt, or should I say, Paulie played by Burt Young is just...
他富有浓厚的…
He's got all... He's got great comic timing skills.
喜剧天分 他很会利用自己的肢体语言
And again he has a unique use of his body
非常独特
that really is very, very special
将他的个性表现得淋漓尽致
and inherent only to his personality.
(CHRISTMAS MUSIC PLAYING ON TV)
他找记者来
ADRIAN: And he called the reporters?
扰乱了我整个训练进度
ROCKY: Yeah. Threw my training schedule off.
别生气 他只是想帮忙
Don't be mad at him. He's trying to help.
艾德丽安 我不生气
Adrian, I ain't mad,
只是记者围在身边
it's just that when reporters are around, I get out of joint
我会有些不知所措 因为他们镜头拍不好 保利也知道
'cause they take cheap shots, and Paulie knows that.
他又一直问我工作的事
And Paulie keeps asking me for a job all the time
可是他对拳击又一窍不通
but he don't know nothing...
我喜欢这一幕
I like this scene.
他内心的怒气已经积累多年
Again, the anger which has been simmering for years
现在开始表现出来了
will start to come to the surface
表现出轻蔑的态度
and the indignity of being taken for granted or pitied...
滚出我的房子！
Get out of my house.
这不只是你的房子
It's not just your house.
他的怒气已经涌现出来 波特很有天分
? explodes to the surface and Burt has amazing volatility.
表演得非常精彩
Very, very explosive man.
保利 外面很冷
It's cold outside, Paulie.
他看起来动作很缓慢
He seems to move slowly,
但这个角色生气的时候 真的很危险
but, when angered, the character is truly dangerous.
这只棒球棍差点就打了下来
This baseball bat came so close to hitting us.
他突然打烂了台灯
Those cups there, everything, just shattered.
我们还没有反应过来
We didn't know where anything was going.
再见
He was like, "Goodbye.''
住手！
Stop it!
我没资格见盖索？ 这就是我对他的看法
I'm not good enough to meet with Gazzo? That's what I think of Gazzo!
你现在是大人物了 连提拔一下朋友都不肯
Now you're a big shot fighter, you don't even throw a crumb to your friend.
我每天早上拿肉给你
When I go and get your meat every morning!
你忘了吗？我连妹妹都许配给你
You forgot that? And then I even give you my sister too!
- 只有猪才会这么说   - 我是猪？
-Only a pig would say that! -I'm a pig?
猪会把最好的都给你？
A pig gets you the best?
我彻底失败了 我为了你不结婚
You're such a loser! I don't get married because of you!
你没办法一个人生活
You can't live by yourself!
我撮合你们 你别想过河拆桥
I put you two together, and don't you forget it!
你欠我的！
You owe me!
我觉得他这一次爆发
I think all of this manifests itself
是因为害怕孤独
because of the fear of loneliness
他的妹妹就像母亲一样
that his sister was like his mother, too.
他是个孩子 会对她依赖
And he is a child when you get right down to it.
她让他精神崩溃
She breaks him right down.
你可以看到这个家到底谁强势
And you see who really had the strength in this family.
这对保利来说是当头棒喝
And it is a painful wakeup call for Paulie.
我不是失败者！
I'm not a loser!
- 你已经破身了   - 什么？
-You're busted! -What?
你已不是处女
You're not a virgin!
你让男人脱你裤子
You let a man take down your pants!
她破身了
She's busted!
我无法控制…
I can't haul meat no more!
原来的剧本当中写的是 洛奇非常生气
In the original draft, Rocky becomes much more intimidating
威肋他说：
and basically threatens him by saying,
“如果你不尊重自己的妹妹”
"If you don't have any respect for your sister
“也该尊重一下我的未来妻子”
"but you better have respect for my future wife,
“下次要是你再敢这样说话 我杀了你” 可我心想：
"or the next time you talk to her like that, I'll kill you.''
这也有点太过火了
And I thought, "Well, that's getting a little heavy-handed.
我觉得洛奇会同情
"I think Rocky would actually be sympathetic
可怜他这位未来的大舅子
"and pity his future brother-in-law,
而不是威肋、他
"rather than threaten him.''
当然
Absolutely.
她已经做好准备向前走
Talia right here looks so confident, she's ready to move on.
面对世界重量级冠军
MICKEY: .the number one heavyweight of the world
你已胸有成竹 对不对？
you'll be ready, won't you?
为什么？因为我等了五十年…
Why? Because I waited for 50 years
让你准备好
to make you ready.
孩子 你有机会奚落他的
You'll be able to spit nails, kid!
就像我说的一样 你要能够快若闪电
Like the guy says, you're gonna eat lightning
气吞奔雷
and you're gonna crap thunder!
你要成为非常危险的对手
You're gonna become a very dangerous person.
这时候米奇充满了活力
What I like bout Mickey here, he's so invigorated.
他的人生再一次得到了一个机会
He's gotten his second wind and his life back.
那是艾尔沙·凡尼
And that is actually Al Silvani,
是一位传奇的拳击教练
who is one of the great legendary cut men of all time.
他训练过许多著名的拳击手 洛基·葛瑞加诺
Who worked with so many of the greats, like Jake LaMotta, Rocky Graziano.
西奥多·马西安诺
Seen it all. And Marciano.
一位真正的传奇人物 他已经去世了 但他的确是真材实料
One of the true legends. He's passed on but he's the real deal.
- 就是因为这样你才会赢   - 听好 他是冠军的料子
-That's why he won. -Listen. We got a winner here.
我们有机会 他的体能是你从未见过的
We got a chance. He goes to the body like nobody you've ever seen.
你只要在一旁待命 我们会赢的
You just stand by. We're gonna win.
我喜欢这个场面 波特不屈不挠
I like this moment a lot, where Burt, he's just unrelenting.
现在他的态度稍微缓和了一点
Now that he's been brought back into the fold, he goes to him,
问他是否想要扬名立万
"You mind if I capitalize on your name, make some money?''
当然了
"No sure, go ahead.''
广告 我对这一行很熟
Advertising. I know about that stuff.
你对广告能懂多少？
What do you know about advertising?
你能赚就去赚 好吗？
Hey, you can make money off my name, make it, okay?
我要去洗澡了
I'm gonna take a shower.
- 帮我解开手套好吗？   - 当然
-Wanna help me off with these? -Sure.
对洛奇来说钱从来都不是问题
Money was never an issue in any of the Rockys
因为他每次参加比赛都不是为了钱
'cause every time we fought, it was never about money.
有波特在帮他 老波特·杨的支票
There he is running with bricks in his hand, an old Burt Young trick.
所以我们只能利用一切能够利用的
So, we'd just grab what we could.
那个朝我扔桔子的人 根本不知道我是谁
That man tossing me an orange had no idea who I was,
不过效果很好
but it worked out great.
这些镜头只是我从货车里跳出来   一路跑
These are just scenes, we'd pull up in a van, jump out, run.
一路拍摄得到的画面
At this point I'm hobbling along because I've probably been running
我跑了好几英里
miles and miles and miles and miles.
我穿过购物中心拍了许多镜头
We'd get so much footage running through shopping malls
但是都没有用到影片当中 因为那些胶片已经丢失了
and things that will never be seen, 'cause the footage doesn't exist anymore.
我们已经用尽了所有训练的方式 他们问：“你还有别的方法吗？"
We were running out of exercises to do. He said, "Do you know anything else?''
我说 “让我试试俯卧撑吧”
I said well, "Let me try some of these push-ups.''
我想在那之前和从那之后 我再也没做过
And I don't think I've done that before or since that day.
这时候的背景音乐很棒
I might add that the music at this point was fantastic.
比尔·康堤用尽一切方法
Bill Conti just came up with a fantastic score
制作出美妙的配乐
on every level.
这些配乐将整部影片…
It just elevated... Whatever transpired visually on film
提升到了一定的高度
was magnified 100 times by the music.
所以我认为他功不可没
So, I compliment his brilliance on that.
你肯定能打败他
You're gonna kill him!
我们从车上跳下来
I remember the van. Here we jumped out of this
觉得这个港口不错 就在这些轮船前面拍跑步的场景吧
and they said, "Oh, there's a nice boat. Let's run by this ship.''
在这个时候
So, at this point I'm about ready to pack it in.
我们已经准备打道回府了
I said, "I can't run much more.''
所以我们就拍了一两遍
I sprinted by this once or twice and...
的确跟配乐很相称
It really capitalized and went well with the song.
又到了这个台阶
We go right to the steps.
这时候手托式摄影机
This is when the Steadicam
的确拍出了不俗的效果
really came into brilliant use.
再没有更好的方式拍摄日落了
There's no other way to have gotten that shot.
“意大利种马登上头条”
“意大利种马”
这时候回到了现实当中
I think there's a point when reality sets in
你必须面对现实
that you've actually talked the talk, walked the walk,
现在你要开始…
and now you're going to be called upon to perform this
在全世界面前表演了
in front of the world.
你真的准备好了吗？
And are you really ready?
在精神上
Mentally.
我们相信你的灵魂
I mean, do you believe it in your soul?
或者你只是在身体上准备好了
Or are you just physically ready,
但还没有做好心理准备
but not intellectually ready to go that distance?
你看到了那么多健壮的拳击手
And you see so many fighters that are physically fit,
但是到了拳击场上 打到一半他们还是倒下了
but they get into the ring, and halfway through they collapse.
他们的意志不够坚强 支撑到胜利
The spirit just abandons them, the will to win,
因为他们心中并没有一团火
because they just don't have that fire in the gut.
而当洛奇走进这个拳击场才发现
And Rocky now realizes, when he walks into this ring,
自己并不是他的对手
that he is so out of his league.
他在俱乐部打拳 参加过十几二十场比赛
He fights in clubs with 13, 15, 19, 25 people.
这让人透不过气 这是克里德的世界
This is just overwhelming. This is Creed's world.
在这里他们搞错了一件事
And they made a mistake here.
我本来打算穿白裤子配红条纹
I was going to wear white trunks with red pants
那天晚上我去的时候
and I showed up that night
发现海报搞错了
and, of course, the poster was wrong.
上面却是红裤子配白条纹
It had red pants, red trunks with a white stripe.
我心想：像溜冰一样
And I thought, like the ice skating rink, maybe we could
我们可以利用这里的环境
make the best out of a situation here.
所以我想 当举办者出现的时候
So I thought, let's have the promoter show up
洛奇说了一句非常天真的话
and Rocky makes a very naive statement.
洛奇
Rocky.
海报画错了
He goes, "The trunks I'm wearing aren't white.''
其实根本没什么关系
He goes, "It really doesn't matter, does it?''
反正不管你穿什么 都会遭到挫败
Insinuating that, "You're gonna get slaughtered,
所以即便你穿内裤出赛都没关系
"so you could wear paisley shorts and it wouldn't matter.''
没什么大碍 不是吗？
It doesn't really matter, does it?
我相信你一定会有精彩演出
I'm sure you're gonna give us a great show.
孩子 好好休息
Try to get some rest, kid.
洛奇的表情好像在说： “反正你也不会在乎”
"Yeah, Rocky, that's like the least of your worries.''
接下来的场面
This scene coming up is
是我一生中的其中一个基准点
one of the benchmarks in my life
因为我们已经没有时间 也没有多少资金了
because we had no time, we had run out of money
全都花在了这一幕上
and the switch was gonna be thrown on this scene, literally.
这时候快要封镜了
The switch is gonna be thrown.
我听到他们说要封镜
When you hear that term, "Well, we're gonna just pull the switch.''
所以我们必须离开那儿
They were pulling the switch because we had to get out of there.
当我走回公寓
And when I walked into the apartment
他们告诉我 已经结束了
I was told, "It's over.''
因为这对我来说是电影里最重要的一幕
I said, "This, to me, is the most important scene in the movie.''
我走进那个房间 躺在床上 必须承认
Going into that house, laying on that bed, he's going to admit
无论如何他都不会打赢的 他没有那种能力
that he cannot win under any situation. He just doesn't have it.
他对自己非常诚实 但他理想的胜利
He's incredibly honest with himself but his idea of victory
和普通人的理想胜利不一样
isn't what a normal fighter's idea of victory is.
他给自己定了一个标准
He's setting a personal standard
也许能够达到
that perhaps he can accomplish.
问题是 我们只能拍一次
The trouble is we had one take to do it in.
然后就要封镜了
And then the switch was gonna be pulled,
所以一旦遇到什么意外 或者出现了机械故障
so if lines had been fumbled or we had camera problems,
那就全完了
it would've been all over.
阿波罗？
Apollo?
很幸运一切顺利
So luckily it all came together.
我一路走一路想
I been out there, walking around, thinking.
我是说我在骗谁？ 我根本是名不见经传
Who am I kidding? I ain't even in the guy's league.
我们该怎么办？
What are we gonna do?
我不知道
I don't know.
你这么努力
You worked so hard.
我们非常的幸运
We were so fortunate on this one.
拍摄的速度正合适
That the camera dollied in at the right pace.
对白也没有弄错
And lines were delivered in the right spots.
我们没有忘记台词 非常幸运
We didn't forget dialogue. Very fortunate.
因为如果没有这一幕 我觉得这部电影
Because without this scene, I don't think the movie
不会达到…
would have accomplished nearly
现在一半的效果
even half of what it set out to accomplish,
表现出…
which is to show
一个男人得到机会 或者一个女人得到机会
that a man given an opportunity, or a woman given an opportunity,
坦诚的表达自己
to express themselves fully,
即使他们知道自己会被打败
even though they know that they're going to be defeated
但即使失败 也虽败犹荣
but in that defeat there can be glory,
个人的光荣
personal glory.
这是我觉得世界上很多人都追求的
And that's what I think so many of... So many people in the world hunger for,
就是一个发挥自己的能力 获得提升或失败的机会
is the opportunity to rise or fail on their own abilities,
只要能获得这个机会
just given the chance.
这再一次表现出了他的恐惧
This was again a little, personal insight here.
卡尔·韦瑟斯饰演的阿波罗·克里德已经准备好了
Carl Weathers of course is mooding up, as Apollo Creed getting ready,
而洛奇穿着一件超大浴袍
and Rocky, they had sent over a bathrobe that was about nine sizes too big.
我觉得很不舒服
And I felt really uncomfortable in it,
好像要把我拽到地上似的
'cause it was, like, dragging down to the floor.
洛奇并没有对比赛全神贯注
So, Rocky, rather than being consumed about the fight,
他想缓解她的紧张感
he's just trying to ease her tensions
对她说不要紧
and saying, "Everything's going to be all right.''
不过我表演得像个孩子
But at the last second, like a child, he goes,
问她：“你会不会觉得这件袍子太大？"
"Do you think this robe is a little baggy?''
艾德丽安 你会不会觉得这件袍子太大？
Adrian, you don't think this robe is too baggy, huh?
祝你好运
Good luck.
别出城
Don't leave town.
我知道观众…
'Cause I figure maybe the audience is saying,
也会认为那件袍子太大
"Boy, that robe looks a little baggy,''
所以我干脆自己说了
so I would just negate that by saying it myself.
谢谢你 上匕尔·鲍德温
Thank you, Bill Baldwin.
今天焦点全集中在洛奇·巴尔博身上
The electricity is all over the place tonight, as Rocky Balboa...
嘿 这是什么玩意？
What is that?
我训练的是拳击手 不是广告招牌
I trained you to be a fighter, not a billboard.
- 我为朋友做的   - 你有什么好处？
-I'm doing it for a friend. -What do you get out of it?
保利得到三千元 袍子归我
Paulie gets$3,000. I get the robe.
真机灵
Shrewd.
关于他们俩不同之处
The story about tonight's fight, their difference in style,
我引述最近一本杂志所写的
you can quote a recent sports magazine which said,
原始人对抗骑士
it could be !!the caveman against the cavalier.!!
我听见欢呼声
I notice a buzzing in the background.
挑战者正要进入比赛场地吗？
Could be the challenger is getting ready to get into the ring.
这么少的预算 很难请到 那么多临时演员担任观众
It was very difficult, on this budget, to get an audience to speak of,
所以这个场面的拍摄
so the way this is filmed
成功的衬托出一个观众席
was very good in suggesting that we had an actual auditorium there,
这些观众其实是…
full of people, when in fact,
我们有两百多人 在周围不同的方向
we had a couple of hundred people that were moved around
拍摄这个场景 所以我们能拍到整个场面
in different directions, to make it seem as though we had a full house.
我觉得有几个镜头穿帮了
There are a couple of cuts which I think don't fit.
有一段场景走道空荡荡的 后期被删除了
They cut to the Madison Square Garden, where they had the Ali-Frazier fight,
因为全场应该有1万5千人
where you had maybe 15,000 people.
有好几个镜头都不太合适
And then it cuts back to ours and it doesn't quite match.
不过这个场面的确不好拍
But somebody's heart was in the right place.
- 袍子背后有肉品广告   - 你看见了吗？
BALDWIN: Some meat sign on the back of his robe. You seen what that was?
Ko.1682.bmp
- 酢酱草肉品   - 酢浆草肉品公司
Shamrock Meat...
背景声音非常嘈杂
There's a lot of noise coming from the background.
你一定会耳聋
Is that the world heavyweight champion, Apollo Creed?
他乘船出场 他是装扮成乔治华盛顿吗？
He's riding in a boat. Is he supposed to be George Washington?
显然是的 他还戴了帽子 你看
Obviously so. He's got the hat on, the whole thing.
我觉得这个主意很棒
This, I thought, worked pretty well.
像剧本里描写的一样
The idea that Carl decided to come into the ring,
卡尔打扮成乔治·华盛顿
or the script decided, to have Carl come into the ring,
隆重登上拳击场 在嘲笑这场比赛
dressed as George Washington just making a joke of the whole situation.
洛奇只不过是个小丑
That Rocky is there as a footnote,
这只是场表演
and it's all about the show.
他现在脱下金色假发及帽子
The hat came off.
他只是为了钱
And about the dough.
观众们是欣喜若狂
The crowd is loving every minute of it.
- 瞧啊 这是世界重量级拳王   - 全世界观众面前
-Here is the world heavyweight champion. -Apollo Creed.
世界拳王阿波罗·克里德
For you around the world
装扮成美国国父乔治华盛顿
he was dressed as George Washington, the father of our country.
为了你们
I want you!
我简直不敢相信我看到的 山姆叔叔本人就在台上
I don't believe what I'm seeing. Uncle Sam himself!
全是为了大家
I want you!
都是为了你们
I want all of you!
在这里洛奇就像个粉丝
And it's noted here that Rocky's like a fan.
他崇拜阿波罗·克里德
There's no... He's applauding. He likes Apollo Creed.
他和观众们一样狂热
He's really enjoying the show as much as anyone in the audience.
他没有受到屈辱的感觉
There's isn't that sense of, "I have to mood up,''
看着他在对自己大吼 他知道自己该怎么做
and he's there and he's snarling and... He knows what he has to do,
为什么不像大家一样享受这一刻
and why not just enjoy the moment like everyone else?
那是他的性格 他就是那样的人
That's just his character. He's one of those kind of guys.
他对对手既不愤慨 也没有敌意
There's no hate, there's no malice for his opponent.
这场比赛 他在孤军奋战
His fight is with himself.
他大喊阿波罗三回合搞定
!!Creed in three.!!
你猜他那套衣服花了多少钱？
What do you think that outfit cost?
女士们 先生们
Ladies and gentlemen.
晚上好
Good evening.
这个人名叫赛瑞尔·戴维
This man's name is Thayer David.
我的一位老友
He played the promoter of course, Miles Jergens.
他是一位非常优秀的演员 他有一种气质
He's a very fine actor and had a certain kind of aplomb about him that...
这就是我刚才说的观众席场面
Here's those Madison Garden shots.
卓越的政界人士
.the many luminaries of politics,
演艺明星…
show business and...
他身上有一种气质 让他看起来很有威严
A certain aplomb about him that gave it a kind of a regal feel.
大多数拳击赛举办人都没有这种特质
Duly noted, most boxing promoters don't have this kind of cachet.
拳坛内外永远的冠军
A champion in and out of the ring,
费城出身的
Philadelphia's own "Smokin' Joe,''
人人仰慕的乔·弗雷泽先生
the beloved Mr. Joe Frazier!
我们再一次超乎意料的
Again, we crossed a line here
请来了费城最著名的拳击手
by bringing in Philadelphia's favorite fighter,
乔·弗雷泽 这是他本人
"Smokin' Joe'' Frazier, the real deal,
由他来向费城拳手
and having him congratulate or give his best wishes to the official
表示祝贺
Philadelphia fighters.
他现在走向拳王
Now he's coming over to talk to the champ.
- 乔 你好   - 你避不见面很久了
-Hey, Joe. -You been ducking me a long time.
开什么玩笑
No, Joe. You're next.
乔 你是下一个
You're next.
在这里卡尔
I thought Carl Weathers was going to get knocked out here
跟他有说有笑
if he kept going with him.
非常精彩
But it was great.
别怯场
Joe Frazier!
来自全球的拳击迷请坐下
-Fight fans, get settled down. -Go home!
因为比赛即将开始
-Don't stay in the arena! -It won't be long now.
在这场比赛当中 有很多动作编排
A lot of choreography went into this fight.
许多拳击电影在这种情况下 都会采用特写镜头
This was a situation where most boxing films are done in extreme close-ups
每一部《洛奇》电影都是如此
and as each Rocky film progressed,
我们希望做得与普通影片当中的 动作编扫卜有所不同
we tried to get further and further away from normal movie choreography,
不是在拳赛过程当中采用大量特写镜头
which would be close-up punches, punches into the camera,
而是让拳击手出现在两个镜头当中
and actually let the fighters go at it in a two-shot.
我非常相信
I'm a big believer
如果在一场比赛当中 只出现一个人的镜头
that the re is no such thing as really a single in a fight.
就会变得更像是电影
That becomes very movie-ish.
而令人无法相信是一场拳赛
It's cinematic in a way that doesn't lend itself to the believability of a fight,
即使在这部影片当中 存在一些这样的镜头
even though we have some in this,
然而在现实当中 是并不存在的
in reality, that doesn't exist.
你 小子 我要你
APOLLO: You, chump. I want you!
你们都在费城比赛过 都已经知道规则
REFEREE: You've both fought in Philadelphia before. You know the rules.
不准打下体 注意头部 不准用头撞击
No low blows, watch your heads, no butting.
双方握手
Shake hands and come out fighting.
小子 把手抬高
Put your hands up there, chump.
- 来打我   - 快点
-Come out fighting. -Come on!
还是没有敌意
Again, no malice.
没有仇恨
No angst.
没有愤怒
No fury.
他只想努力坚持完比赛 离开赛场 仅此而已
Just trying to survive, go the distance, and that's it.
他对自己的能力没有幻想
He has no illusions about his ability
从没想过要控制住对手
to dominate this man, never gonna happen.
第一回合钟声响了
BALDWIN: There's the bell for round one.
参赛者走到拳击台中央
The fighters come in the center of the ring, looking at each other.
卡尔的拳击技巧很精湛
Carl Weathers had really fantastic boxing abilities.
对于一个从来没真正参加过 拳击赛的人来说 他的快拳 强壮的体魄
For a man who never really boxed, just a quick jab, strong body,
漂亮的足下动作 他是一位优秀的运动员
fantastic foot movement, he's just a great athlete.
我想世界上没有一个人 会比他演得更好
I don't think anyone on the planet could have done it better.
我知道我们非常非常幸运
I know they couldn't. We were very, very lucky.
其实他并非第一选择
He wasn't even the first choice.
我们的第一选择是一位叫 凯恩·莫顿的拳击手
The first choice was a fighter named Ken Norton,
他是为真正的拳击冠军 块头很大
who was a world champion and very, very large.
他接到这个角色 我记得是开拍前的那晚 或是前一晚
He had the job and, I think, the night before or two nights before,
他说 “我不想演 我演不了 报酬太少了”
he said, "I don't want to do it. I can't do it. It's not paying enough.''
我问他 “你想干什么？"
I said, "Well, what do you want to do?''
他说 "A BC电台有一场超级明星拳赛”
He goes, "Well.. There's an ABC superstar competition.''
一个电视节目 他选择了那个
Some television show, and that's what he chose to do.
就像命中注定一样
And as fate would have it,
下一个走进来的人 就是卡尔·韦瑟斯
the next guy who walked in the door was Carl Weathers,
他正打算回奥克兰
who was on his way back to Oakland,
如果我们不是及时打电话给他
and if we hadn't have called him at a certain time,
他可能也没法出演
he wouldn't have been available.
我们也没法看到他的精彩表演
We never would have known he existed.
我们只是得到了第二次机会
It was just split-second timing.
正好在对的时候遇到了对的人 我们很幸运
He happened to be in the right place at the right time. Lucky for us.
这是拳王第一次被击倒
NAHAN: The referee is giving him the count.
六 七 八
Six, seven, eight.
他似乎没事
He appears to be all right. Glassy-eyed but okay.
洛奇 打他的肋骨
MICKEY: Go to the ribs! Go to work, Rock!
我感到很惊讶 这时候观众们…
I was surprised at this point at the audience.
非常兴奋 我们知道 这里很有看头
They're very excited, and we knew that we had something going on here,
因为他们心里相信 这是场真正的拳赛
because they were buying into the fight, on an emotional level.
我相信拳击赛是非常微妙的
And I believe fights are very, very delicate,
动作的设计和编扫卜
the way they are choreographed, the way they are laid out.
出拳太多或出拳太少
Too many punches, too few punches,
不是让观众眼花缭乱
you can either get to the saturation point
就有可能让观众感到麻木 他们就会走神
or the point where you just desensitize people and they no longer pay attention.
所以必须设计一个合理的速度和节奏
So, you have to create a give and a take and an ebb and a flow
像一场真正的精彩赛事一样 不断提起观众的兴趣
that continues to keep the audience interested like a great fight would.
有时随意出几拳 上匕如打中面颊
Just random, throwing the punches, like just a little tap on the cheek,
会让场面看起来更真实
makes it more personal and more insulting than a big punch.
…极欲赢得比赛
Do your best. Do your best.
阿波罗出左拳击中对手
NAHAN: Apollo unloading a left.
我们设计洛奇的鼻子被对手打断
Now we were set up where Rocky gets his nose broken,
他一小时前的生气
which we set up an hour earlier, and that was his badge of pride.
现在完全消失了
Now it's gone.
他把洛奇逼至角落 洛奇几乎搞不清方向
They're leading him to his corner. Rocky can't find his way.
开始有点吃不消
Welcome to the big league.
阿波罗 阿波罗！
I called it!
你的鼻梁断了
-Your nose is broke. -How's it look?
- 看起来怎么样？   - 需要整型一下
It's an improvement.
不要再搅和了 我要你移动 多出重拳
Quit shucking and jiving! Stick and move!
打肋骨 不要让那小子喘息
Go for the ribs. Don't let that bastard breathe.
他真的很棒
The guy's quick.
他不知道这是作秀 他以为是场拳赛
He doesn't know it's a damn show. He thinks it's a damn fight.
- 赶快解决他然后回家   - 好的
Finish this bum, and let's go home.
贴近他 你表现得很棒
Stay to the body. You're doing great!
第二回合开始
Round two. Creed predicted he'd win in it in three.
拳王说他会在三回合内胜利
Creed got knocked down in the first. He came back strong.
我很相信人生
I'm a big believer in life, you know, they say,
你只有不断拼搏才能往上爬
"You have to keep punching to stay on top in life,''
我相信生活总是会给人带来磨难
and I believe that life always punches a lot harder than you punch
只有能够接受磨难的人
and the man who can take a punch,
能够克服磨难的人 才能往前走
can absorb a punch and keep going,
无论是在生活中 还是在拳击场上 这样的人才是最危险的对手
either in life or in the ring itself, really is the dangerous opponent.
任何人都能出拳 很少人能承受
Anybody can throw, very few can take it.
所以他低估了洛奇的承受能力
And that's where he underestimated Rocky's ability to absorb punishment,
你越是打他
and the more you hit him,
他就会越勇猛
the more he stiffens his resolve.
洛奇试图反击 他把拳王逼至角落
Balboa trying to fight back. Oh, he tagged the champ!
拳王试图要脱困
The champion is trying...
这些镜头非常精彩 我们花了很长时间排练
Here we go, this was some good moving. We spent a lot of time just firing away,
许多上肢猛击的动作都很危险
and a lot of those body punches are landing. Those, by the way,
顺便一提 他戴的是8盎司重的拳击手套
are, for boxing aficionados, those are eight-ounce gloves,
现在对于重量级选手来说是非法的
that are now considered illegal for heavyweights.
因为太危险了
They're just too dangerous.
不管你用那种手套打中哪里 都会剧痛无比
So, anything you hit with those, hurts immensely.
连续攻击
Ebb and flow, ebb and flow.
现在你可以看到阿波罗·克里德 终于沉不住气了
I love it when you see Apollo Creed now,
他有过很多经验
finally, he's learning a lot about himself.
却从来没参加过这样的比赛
He's never been in this kind of battle in his life.
洛奇被打得脚步不稳
He got tagged!
裁判插进来一下
The referee's wiping off the gloves.
又是左右一轮重拳
Hard left and right combination!
比尔 是什么原因让他不倒下 我不知道
-What is keeping him up, Bill? -l don't know.
他连拳套都抬不起来
He can't even get his gloves up to protect himself.
这一拳重重的击中了我的下巴
Some of these would really catch me underneath my chin.
真的很痛
And they would sting. Boy, they would sting.
趴下 别起来
Down! Stay down!
阿波罗双拳高举 得意万分
Apollo has his arms in the air!
五…
Five.
比尔·康提的音乐将影片 提升到另一个高度
Bill Conti's music just elevated this to majestic heights.
九…
Nine.
被打成那样的人 还有毅力站起来继续比赛
After giving a man a beating like that, it's got to discourage anyone, even Apollo,
噢 天啊 他还有多少精力？
"Oh, my God, what's it gonna take?''
这就是在冷冻室训练的结果 打肋骨
This is where the payoff at the meat house comes in, the ribs.
肋骨 肋骨 肋骨
The ribs, the ribs and the ribs.
拳王肋骨被左拳击中
The champion got a left to his right ribs.
他付出的努力终于得到了回报
A little foreshadowing that paid off
这一拳可不轻
Okay, champ?
拳王 你还好吗？
Yeah, I'm okay.
没事 我还好
I may have broke my ribs.
不要紧
我看不见 帮我把眼睛张开
I can't see nothing. Gotta open my eye.
很多人对这一幕都很担心
This caused some people
要把眼睛割开 在赛场上真的会这么做
a lot of concern, the cutting of the eye, and this is something they used to do.
我的天
Oh, God.
在50年代 他们会把眼皮割开 把血放出来
In the '50s, they would just literally lance the eye to get the blood out.
而这种事现在是绝对不会发生的
By today's standards, that would never, ever happen.
他们会被吊销执照的
They would lose their license.
但以前的确是这么做的
But it did happen in the old days.
这个人会继续比赛
And these men would go on in battle above and beyond
将生死置之度外
any kind of physical safety,
因为他们的求胜欲非常强烈
'cause their hearts were just so big, and their desire to win so overwhelming,
他们将个人安危都放在一边
that their personal concerns were on the back burner.
他们俩好像经历一场战争
They look like they've been in a war.
这是我的代表作
There goes my mouthpiece.
拳王好重的一拳
The champion really tagged him.
很明显阿波罗在保护他的右侧
Apollo clearly protecting his right side, his ribs.
左勾拳
Body punches!
- 看他身上流出来的血   - 他在吐血了
Hard lefts and rights. Look at the blood coming out of his mouth!
阿波罗的忍受能力也很强
Carl was really good at being able to take and sell a punch.
他的身体可以承受
His body would just contort.
洛奇 加油
Go for it, Rock!
听听观众的震天喊声…
-Listen to this crowd! -Right to the ribs.
又一记重拳 直接击中脸颊
Another to the ribs. That left hand again.
他想知道是否还有另外＋秒钟
I'm wondering if they had gone another 10 seconds...
他把拳王逼至角落
Apollo the champ...
(BELL CLANGING)
不会再重赛 不会在重赛
Ain't gonna be no rematch.
我不要重赛
Don't want one.
这时候 洛奇的比赛结束了
Now, Rocky, at this point, his fight is over.
他已经不再关心结果
He has no concern for the decision.
不管是输是赢还是打和
He doesn't know if he won or he lost, if it was a draw.
他的意志已经取胜了 他仍然站在那儿
He won in his mind. He's standing up.
他唯一想做的
And his concerns are only
就是回到他最爱的女人身边
to get the object of his desire, the woman he loves the most,
希望他唯一爱的女人 能与他分享这一刻
the only woman he loves, in there to share this moment.
这时候他的心里只有她
It's all about her at this time.
其实我们已经用尽了资金
We actually ran out of money,
本该重拍这个场面
and had to re-shoot this scene.
无论你是否相信 我们只有30名临时演员
And believe it or not, we only had about 30 extras.
这是最初拍摄的场景
And what we did is, this is the original scene
但洛奇的这个特写镜头 是两个月之后拍的
but the close-up of Rocky right there, this was done two months later.
我们只拍了拳击场的一角 围绳和其中一角
And we only had a little corner of the ring, one corner of it, just the ropes,
让人们围成一圈
and people would circle around,
我们让制片人恰托夫和温克勒
and had the producers and Chartoff and Winkler,
还有亲戚和朋友 以及 所有我们认识的人
and friends and family and anyone we could ask
在某个下午聚集在那里
to stand there for an afternoon. Right there, these shots.
重新创造这个时刻 因为最初的结尾是他离开拳击场
To recreate this moment 'cause originally it ended outside the ring,
走进更衣室
walking to the dressing room, and I thought,
我觉得效果不好 也许我们应该在此结束
"This is not working, maybe we should end it right he re,
在他最兴奋的时刻 以及她的爱的围绕下
"at the height of his exaltation and his love of her.''
影片在他人生的顶峰结束
Just freeze it at the pinnacle of his life.
这是个美好的经历
It's been a wonderful ride.